<?xml-model href="ODD/out/AntarcticDraft.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?><?xml-model href="ODD/out/AntarcticDraft.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter Volume 2 Issue 6</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Florida State University, Office of Digital Research and Scholarship</publisher>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">Attribution 2.0 Generic (CC BY 2.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <placeName>Tallahassee, Florida</placeName>
                  <institution>Florida State University</institution>
                  <!-- INCLUDE (as collection) -->
                  <collection>Robert E. Hancock Jr. Antarctic Collection</collection>
                  <!-- INCLUDE (as iid) -->
                  <idno type="IID">FSU_MSS_1976022_B07_F01_V2I6</idno>
=
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <!-- INCLUDE (as title) -->
                     <title>Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter Volume 2 Issue 6</title>
                     <!-- INCLUDE (as author) -->
                     <author>United States. Naval Support Force, Antarctica</author>
                     <!-- INCLUDE  (as docdate; @when)-->
                     <docDate when="1957-05-17">May 17, 1957</docDate>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="1"/>
         <div type="nameplate">
            <head style="text-decoration: underline; text-align: center; text-transform: uppercase;">Operation Deep Freeze <choice>
                  <sic>Newslatter</sic>
                  <corr>Newsletter</corr>
               </choice>
                </head>
            <lb/>
            <ab>
               <num type="volume" value="2">Volume II</num>, <num type="issue" value="6">No. 6</num>
               <date when="1975-05-17">May 17,1957</date>
            </ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="NAFMcMurdo">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">NAF MCMURDO</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-05-14">May
                  14</date>) -- A blizzard struck this base today, with 28 hours of 38-knot winds or
               above. The highest average hourly velocity was 50 knots, and peak gusts reached 82.5
               knots.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Hardest hit were wires and antennas, but a minimum of building damage was sustained.
               A rundown of damage is as follows:</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>Seventy-five foot pole down in feed-in end of Balboa Rhombic; Balboa Rhombic wire
               down; New Zealand Rhombic wire down; Palmer Peninsula doublet loosened and split in
               middle; north-south and east-west doublets loosened; all Rhombic poles have <choice>
                  <sic>aminimum</sic>
                  <corr>a minimum</corr>
               </choice> of two guys each detached, and some poles are held up by one guy only;
               approximately 1,000 feet of all transmission lines down with standoff insulators
               snapped and remaining transmission lines loosened considerably; tarpaulin on false
               roof of transmitter building partly blown off; snow entered transmitter building and
               found way into some transmitters, but equipment was off at time; one power line pole
               down; approximately 800 feet of power line down; nine stations on the power amplifier
               system inoperative; various guy wire failures and resulting 75-foot pole collapse due
               to turnbuckle loosening and finally paring as a result of vibration in guy wires by
               high winds.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Estimated completion date for damage repair is <date when="1957-06-07">June
               7</date>, depending upon the weather.</ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="SouthPoleStation">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#SouthPoleStation">SOUTH POLE STATION</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-05-11">May 11</date>) -- According to data and records available at
               this station, a new world's low temperature record was established at the <placeName ref="#SouthPoleStation">South Pole</placeName> today. At 2:30p.m. (Greenwich,
               England, time; 9:30 a.m. EST) the official temperature registered 100째 below
               zero Fahrenheit, marking the low point of two days of steadily falling
               temperature.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>The previous record low was recorded in the northern Siberian village of Verkoyansk
               in February, 1892, when the thermometer there descended to 90 degrees below
               zero.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>The temperature inside the tunnels surrounding and interconnecting the buildings lags
               behind the temperature outside, but it was already close in -72째. Moist air from
               the buildings causes dense fog in the tunnels, reducing visibility to a matter of
               yards.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Outside the air was perfectly clear as the moon slowly rose above the horizon to
               cast the only natural light (other than starlight and the Aurora Australis) that will
               be seen here until the return of the sun on <date when="1957-08-23">Sept.
               23</date>.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <ab>The normal routine of the 18 men manning the South Pole continued despite
               difficulties imposed by the decreasing temperature, and knowing that the thermometer
               will probably drop another 20 degrees.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <ab>By the calendar, winter does not officially begin until <date when="1957-06-21">June
                  21</date>, but the frost is already on the "punkins."</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <ab>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-05-12">May 12</date>) -- Simultaneous with the establishment of the
               world's lowest official temperature record of -100째 Fahrenheit at the <placeName ref="#SouthPoleStation">South Pole Station</placeName>, <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName> experienced a record-breaking
               "heat wave."</ab>
            <lb/>
            <ab>On <date when="1957-05-11">May 11</date> the thermometer at Little America
               registered plus 30째F., a difference of 130 degrees within a distance of
               approimately 700 nautical miles.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <fw>-- <num type="page" value="1">1</num> --</fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="2"/>
            <lb/>
            <ab>The previous all-time high temperature recorded for May at <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName> was plus 25 degrees F.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>Accompanying the high temperature were record-breaking May gale winds of 60 miles per
               hour. The previous all-time record for May at <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little
                  America</placeName> was 47 miles per hour.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Heat waves and wind bring more problems to <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little
                  America</placeName> than does cold weather. The roofs of buildings are not
               constructed to be absolutely waterproof because the exterior roof temperature is
               below freezing most of the year, thus presenting no problem of leakage. During
               unusual warm spells such as this, snow melts on the roof surfaces, creating multiple
               leaks inside.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Also some buildings in sheltered areas of the camp have difficulty keeping cool
               enough at such times. With the heater control turned to the lowest position,
               buildings still overheat, thus attesting to effective design for extreme cold and
               efficient insulation.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>High winds blow snow into mountainous drifts. A portion of the new chapel, only three
               weeks old, is already inundated beneath five feet of snow above roof level. The
               current storm covered the chimney completely, necessitating the heater to be turned
               off until the stack can be dug out.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>It seems ironical to wish for cold weather in the Antarctic winter, but such is the
               case at <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName> today.</ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- The organization of
               Deep Freeze II began just over a year ago, <date when="1956-05-08">May 8,
               1956</date>, when MCB Special, Detachment Bravo, was established upon dispatch
               authority from COMCBLANT. Approximately 60 Bravo personnel had reported for duty.
                  <persName ref="#WilliamFFlynn">CDR William F. Flynn</persName> and five officers
               were present.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Everyone upon arrival was given thorough physical and mental examinations, offices
               were being set up and personnel were being deployed to all parts of the country for
               specialized training.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>Looking back, the wholehearted cooperation and encouragement of COMCBLANT in
               supporting the new organizations was outstanding. Without their help our preparatory
               work at Davisville would have been infinitely more difficult and less efficient.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Looking ahead one year, we shall all probably be back in the States recounting to
               families and friends our experiences in Antarctica, and Deep Freeze II will have
               become history.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <ab>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-05-11">May 11</date>) -- "Operation Treasure Hunt" was suggessful in
               the fading twilight last week.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>Prospectors of the old Yukon had nothing on VX-6 detachment at <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName>. Although not hunting gold, local
               airdales were after treasure in the form of precious spare parts for aircraft--much
               more valuable down here than gold.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Last year on Deep Freeze I supplies had to be moved in a matter of hours from a
               chache on the bay ice to the camp site when ice unexpectedly broke up and floated to
               sea. Much confusion was unaviodable. It was impossible to make accurate records or
               charts of the location of various supply dumps. Blizzards soon covered everything
               with snow.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Everything within 100 yards of the camp perimeter was now completely lost. In any
               direction the snow surface looked the same--perpetual, gently-sloping drifts. Visual
               inspection and random probing yielded nothing.</p>
            <lb/>
            <fw>-- <num type="page" value="2">2</num> --</fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="3"/>
            <p>After a study by <persName ref="#HarveyGSpeed">LT Harvey G. Speed</persName> of
                  <placeName ref="#NorthMuskegonMI">North Muskegon, Mich</placeName>, of aerial
               photos taken last year, <persName ref="#JamesEWaldron">LCDR James E. Waldron,
                  Jr.</persName>, of <placeName ref="#NewOrleansLA">New Orleans, La.</placeName>,
               decided to explore certain clues in hope of locating missing spare parts. Supervised
               by <persName ref="#HarveyGSpeed">Lt Speed</persName> and <persName ref="#RobertGAnderson">Lt Robert G. Anderson</persName> of <placeName ref="#AlamedaCA">Alameda, Calif.</placeName>, the crew began prospecting. After
               measuring angles and distances from permanent buildings, the areas of greatest
               probability were staked out. These were combed with a mine detector which proved of
               little value since the penetration signal into the snow was too shallow.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>At this point a D-8 Caterpillar tractor, piloted by <persName ref="#DemarEWard">Demar
                  E. Ward, Jr.</persName>, Construction Driver 1/c, of <placeName ref="#FortSmithAR">Fort Smith, Ark.</placeName>, was called in. Slowly, almost gingerly, he pushed
               great drifts of snow aside. Suddenly a crate appeared. Tractor operations were halted
               and a "Mexican drag line" (long handled shovels) was manned by <persName ref="#BernestGMelton">Bernest G. Melton</persName>, aviation machinist's mate 1/c
               of <placeName ref="#WadesboroNC">Wadesboro, N.C.</placeName> and <persName ref="#JamesCLeischner">James C. Leischner</persName>, Aviation electronics
               technician 3/c of <placeName ref="#CiscoIL">Cisco, Ill</placeName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="article">
            <p>AROUND THE BASES -- (<date when="1957-05-13">May 13</date>) -- <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName>: The Little America University of
               Antarctica is in session with couress in calculus, Spanish, photography, bible study,
               choir and drama. Further courses are planned. Recreation hall is 80% completed.
               Tractor train load test underway. Received a broadcast from the Russian base, Mirny,
               of a Radio Moscow tape recording for <persName ref="#VladimirRastorguev">
                        <choice>
                     <sic>Valdimir</sic>
                     <corr>Vladimir</corr>
                  </choice> Rastorguev</persName>, Russian observer and Meteorologist here. Post
               office moved from the Rec. Hall to Bldg. 5, publicworks building....... <placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">NAF McMurdo</placeName>: Deck completed and Quonset frames up
               for temporary building (garage) .... <placeName ref="#CapeAdare">Adare</placeName>:
               Lack of tunnel system requires digging out after storms...... <placeName ref="#SouthPoleStation">South Pole</placeName>: All communications equipment
               installed. Glaciology cold lab completed ..... <placeName ref="#WilkesStation">Wilkes</placeName>: One weasel modified for use as a fire engine with large
               ladders and fire fighting gear installed. Sixteen by twenty foot wooden shelter
               erected for photo storage and general <choice>
                  <sic>stowage</sic>
                  <corr>storage</corr>
               </choice>.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- <date when="1957-05-11">May 11</date> -- The Antarctic Beard Club of Little America a growing the
               bushiest crop of whiskers and the widest variety of beards imaginable. Organized last
               January by <persName ref="#CharlesMDarter">Charles M. Darter</persName>, Chief
               Construction Driver, of <placeName ref="#AustinTX">Austin, Texas</placeName>;
                  <persName ref="#KennethAElliot">Kenneth A. Elliot</persName>, Construction Driver
               1/c of <placeName ref="#LancasterPA">Lancaster, Pa.</placeName>; <persName ref="#StevenMuniz">Steven Muniz</persName>, Construction Driver 2/c of <placeName ref="#SugarCityCO">Sugar City, Colo.</placeName>; and <persName ref="#SterkelLCoyne">Sterkel L. Coyne</persName>, Construction Driver 3/c of
                  <placeName ref="#PiquaOH">Piqua, Ohio</placeName>; the club has expanded to 17
               members.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Two qualifications for membership are: Individual must be "man enough" to grow a
               beard (moustache alone is insufficient), and the man must vow not to shave until he
               reaches the United States. If the man shaves or permits his beard</ab>
            <lb/>
            <fw>-- <num>3</num> --</fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="4"/>
            <ab>to be removed prior to arrival in the U.S., he must pay a penalty of $5 to every
               other member. At present this would cost $80.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <ab>There are, however, two exceptions to the rule: If the man is directed by the
               medical officer to shave for health reasons, or if ordered to shave by competent
               military authority before arrival in the U.S.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>The senior club member is <persName ref="#WillieMDickey">Capt W. Mills
                  Dickey</persName>, commander of Naval Support Units, Antarctica, of <placeName ref="#RuskTX">Rusk, Texas</placeName>. Other members, in addition to the
               organizers, are <persName ref="#RobertSBallou">Robert S. Ballou</persName>, Radioman
               3/c, of <placeName ref="#RoanokeVA">Roanoke, Va.</placeName>; <persName ref="#HaroldDKCrain">Harold D. K. Crain</persName>, Utilitiesman 3/c, of
                  <placeName ref="#MontoursvillePA">Montoursville, Pa.</placeName>; <persName ref="#ForrestEDurnell">Forrest E. Durnell</persName>, Storekeeper 1/c of
                  <placeName ref="#IndependenceMO">Independence, Mo.</placeName>; <persName ref="#BobbieFGrice">Bobbie F. Grice</persName>, Radioman 1/c, of <placeName ref="#HubbardTX">Hubbard, Texas</placeName>; <persName ref="#JulianPGudmunson">Julian P. Gudmunson</persName>, Chief Builder, of <placeName ref="#StPaulMN">St.
                  Paul, Minn.</placeName>; <persName ref="#RobertEJones">Robert E. Jones</persName>,
               Construction Driver 2/c, of <placeName ref="#SurquinsvilleTN">Surquinsville,
                  Tenn.</placeName>; <persName ref="#HectorKLett">Hector K. Lett</persName>,
               Construction Driver 3/c, of <placeName ref="#KnoxvilleTN">Knoxville,
                  Tenn.</placeName>; <persName ref="#JerryFMann">Jerry F. Mann</persName>,
               Utilitiesman 3/c, of <placeName ref="#QuincyIL">Quincy, Ill.</placeName>; <persName ref="#FranklinOStackhouse">Franklin O. Stackhouse</persName>, Chief Aviation
               Electronics Technician, of <placeName ref="#MeadbillePA">Meadbille, Pa.</placeName>;
                  <persName ref="#BernardFVerboncouer">Bernard F. Verboncouer</persName>, Chief
               Quartermaster, of <placeName ref="#GreenBayWI">Green Bay, Wisc.</placeName>;
                  <persName ref="#DemarEWard">Demar E. Ward</persName>, Jr., Construction Driver
               1/c, of <placeName ref="#FortSmithAR">Fort Smith, Ark.</placeName>; and <persName ref="#WilliamJWilliams">William J. Williams, Jr.</persName>, Chief Radioman, of
                  <placeName ref="#HarlingenTX">Harlingen, Tex.</placeName>
                </p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Many people growing beards have not joined the club. The current total is 76 beards,
               six moustaches and 27 clean-shaven faces. The beards are now long enough for
               trimming. Interesting styles include Van Dyke, mutton chop, goatee, and handlebar
               moustache, in addition to natural growth.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>All beards must be well groomed, requiring frequent shampoos, brushing and combing.
               The consensus of opinion is that to have a beard is more time consuming than to
               shave. Most personnel working outside prefer a beard. It seems to keep the face
               warmer even though the breath condenses and forms ice on the surface of the beard.
               It's believed that air trapped in the beard next to the face provides insulation.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Colors of the beards are sometimes surprising. <persName ref="#FranklinOStackhouse">Chief Stackhouse</persName> has dark hair but a red beard. <persName ref="#WillieMDickey">Capt Dickey</persName> and <persName ref="#BernardFVerboncouer">Chief Verboncouer</persName> have jet black beards
               marked by sharply defined vertical silver panels approximately one and a half inches
               in the moustache and chin. <persName ref="#JohnEZoller">Chaplain John E.
                  Zoller</persName> of <placeName ref="#ShelbyMI">Shelby, Mich.</placeName>, has
               dark hair but a gray, almost white, beard.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Texture of some beards is soft and silky, while others are wiry and a few are just
               fuzz. Some are straight, some wavy and some curly. A few men have recently "come
               clean" and shaved. It's a startling change in appearance, almost unrecognizable at
               first. This causes many to speculate if families and friends would recognize them
               wearing a beard. Some will rely on photos to show their families, while others plan
               to wear their beards home if military authority permits.</p>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <fw>-- <num type="page" value="4">4</num> --</fw>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
