<?xml-model href="ODD/out/AntarcticDraft.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?><?xml-model href="ODD/out/AntarcticDraft.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter Volume 2 Issue 5</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Florida State University, Office of Digital Research and Scholarship</publisher>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">Attribution 2.0 Generic (CC BY 2.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <placeName>Tallahassee, Florida</placeName>
                  <institution>Florida State University</institution>
                  <!-- INCLUDE (as collection) -->
                  <collection>Robert E. Hancock Jr. Antarctic Collection</collection>
                  <!-- INCLUDE (as iid) -->
                  <idno type="IID">FSU_MSS_1976022_B07_F01_V2I5</idno>
                  =
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <!-- INCLUDE (as title) -->
                     <title>Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter Volume 2 Issue 5</title>
                     <!-- INCLUDE (as author) -->
                     <author>United States. Naval Support Force, Antarctica</author>
                     <!-- INCLUDE  (as docdate; @when)-->
                     <docDate when="1957-05-10">May 10, 1957</docDate>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="1"/>
         <div type="nameplate">
            <head style="text-decoration: underline; text-align: center; text-transform: uppercase;">Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter</head>
            <ab>
               <num type="volume" value="2">Volume II, </num>
                    <num type="issue" value="5"> No.
                  5</num>
               <date when="1957-05-10">May 10, 1957</date>
                </ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <ab>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America's</placeName> "ice dentists" are at work again
               filling a cavity in a crevasse.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>One mile from camp on the road to the barrier it is necessary to cross a mysterious
               creeping crevasse. This is the <choice>
                  <sic>eight</sic>
                  <corr>eighth</corr>
               </choice> time the crevasse has been filled since January. It keeps opening and no
               one knows what happens to the hundreds of tons of snow which are used to fill it each
               time.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The crevasse is like a jagged gorge approximately 50 feet deep, crossing the road at
               a 90° angle. By descending on a rope ladder to the bottom of the crevasse, a man
               can walk one quarter mile in either direction from the road, hemmed in by the
               towering cliffs of glistening blue granite-like ice, varying from 10 to 20 feet
               apart.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>A man's first trip into such a crevasse is fascinating but terrifying. The ghostly
               silence is overwhelming and unnerving. But the silence is not prolonged, for
               intermittently one will hear a deep rumble, muffled booming, rasping groan or sharp,
               cracking, splintering sounds. It is the imperceptible movement of the ice, as if it
               were wincing in excruciating pain under the relentless pressure of its own weight,
               aggravated by the perpetually undulating sea beneath. This, combined with a feeling
               of utter impotence should the walls of ice give away (which the eerie sounds seem to
               suggest) will reduce all but the bravest souls to flight.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>On <date when="1957-04-28">April 28</date> the oceanographic study group reported a
               crack 18 inches wide across the road upon their return from the barrier. This was a
               tipoff of an open crevasse beneath, transforming the road into a booby trap.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The next day, in minus 54° weather whipped by a 15-knot wind, a repair team
               composed of <persName ref="#HowardJOrndorff">LCDR Howard J. Orndorff</persName>,
               Officer in Charge of Little America, of <placeName ref="#NutterfortWV">Nutterfort, W.
                  Va.</placeName>; <persName ref="#RobertKWhite">LTJG Robert K. White</persName> of
                  <placeName ref="#GlenFallsNY">Glen Falls, N.Y.</placeName>; <persName ref="#JulianPGudmunson">Julian P. Gudmunson</persName>, Chief <choice>
                  <sic>Buioder</sic>
                  <corr>Builder</corr>
               </choice> , of <placeName ref="#StPaulMN">St. Paul, Minn.</placeName>; <persName ref="#CharlesMDarter">Charles M. Darter</persName>, Chief Construction Driver, of
                  <placeName ref="#AustinTX">Austin, Texas</placeName>; <persName ref="#RobertWAnderson">Robert W. Anderson</persName>, Electronics Technician 3/c,
               of <placeName ref="#WhiteCityKS">White City, Kan.</placeName>; and <persName ref="#AlvinLMiller">Alvin L. Miller</persName>, Construction Driver 2/c, of
                  <placeName ref="#MiltonFL">Milton, Fla.</placeName>; tackled the job armed with
               dynamite and a D-8 tractor.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#RobertWAnderson">Anderson</persName> is a veteran of conquering
               crevasses, having explored approximately 100 of them last November when blazing the
               647 mile trail to <placeName ref="#ByrdStation">Byrd Station</placeName>. He
               sometimes swung at the end of a 50-foot rope like a pendulum, planting blasting
               charges at the most vulnerable spot deep in the jaws of a crevasse.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>
                    <persName ref="#JulianPGudmunson">Gudmunson</persName> is a seasoned expert in ice
               blasting, having worked as right hand man to <persName ref="#MerleRDawson">Arctic
                  Specialist MAJ Merle R. Dawson</persName>, <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesArmyReserves">USAR</orgName>, last January when they changed the
               face of the barrier by carving a berth for cargo ships, and in the process creating
               what might have been the first man-made Antarctic icebergs.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#AlvinLMiller">Miller</persName> is a versatile, <choice>
                  <sic>indefatigible</sic>
                  <corr>indefatigable</corr>
               </choice> worker and hardened to intense cold by daily exposure. He drove a D-8
               tractor on a 1300 mile record round-trip to <placeName ref="#ByrdStation">Byrd
                  Station</placeName>.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Like capable dentists the repair team proceeded to clean the cavity carefully before
               filling. Eight blasts later all were aghast at the yawning chasm before them which a
               short time earlier had been the road. In the dim</ab>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="2"/>
            <ab>light of the sunless Antarctic winter dusk, <persName ref="#CharlesMDarter">Darter</persName> mounted his roaring iron monster, clicked on the floodlights
               and began pushing mountainous heaps of snow into the crevasse. With the touch of a
               genius he handled the gargantuan tractor as if it were a toy, advancing to the lip of
               the crevasse, then watching the snow cascade like a tumbling white waterfall into the
               abyss below.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>Final phase of the operation was to pack the snowfill solid by running the 38-ton
               tractor over it numerous times. Now the road is as good as new. Once again the
               spectacular has been the routine in the Antarctic.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article">
            <ab>HAM RADIO ASSISTANCE OFFERED -- A letter was received this week from <persName ref="#GeorgeCKanney">Mr. George C. Kanney</persName> of <placeName ref="#LaPorteIN">LaPorte, Indiana</placeName>, a "ham" radio operator who is
               interested in lending assistance to Deep Freeze men in Antarctica and their families
               at home.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <ab>
                    <persName ref="#GeorgeCKanney">Mr. Kanney</persName> says "...I have a schedule with
               station KC4USB every night (<placeName ref="#ByrdStation">Byrd
               Station</placeName>)...and would be glad to handle any traffic for the scientists or
               personnel at this station for about four months."</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#GeorgeCKanney">Mr. Kanney</persName> operates amateur station W9ETM.
               Anyone interested in taking advantage of his generous offer is invited to contact
                  <persName ref="#GeorgeCKanney">Mr. Kanney</persName> at <address>
                  <street>412 Woodson St.</street>
                  <placeName ref="#LaPorteIN">, LaPorte, Indiana.</placeName>
               </address>
                </p>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="NAFMcMurdo">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">NAF MCMURDO</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-05-08">May
                  8</date>) -- Construction crews here have worked five 24-hour days to complete the
               first in a series of buildings which will replace the garage destroyed by fire <date when="1957-04-28">April 28</date>. The <orgName ref="#UntiedStatesNavyConstructionBattalions">Seabees</orgName> met the five-day
               schedule set by themselves, in spite of difficult weather conditions and a shortage
               of adequate materials and tools.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>The finished building will house the garage, carpenter, machine, welding, and
               electrician shops, and a spare parts room.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Other <placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">McMurdo</placeName> residents have turned their
               talents to gardening.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#WilliamFFlynn">CDR William F. Flynn</persName>, Commanding Officer of
               MCB Special, of <placeName ref="#DedhamMA">Dedham, Mass.</placeName>; <persName ref="#ScottWMarshall">LCDR Scott W. Marshall</persName>, Officer in Charge of
               McMurdo, of <placeName ref="#WichitaKS">Wichita, Kan.</placeName>; and <persName ref="#MartinKHanson">Martin K. Hanson</persName>, Chief Construction Driver, of
                  <placeName ref="#SiouxFallsND">Sioux Falls, N.D.</placeName>, have succeeded in
               producing radishes, believed to be the first grown in the Antarctic. Various seeds
               and plants have been carefully nurtured by the gardeners in a box garden located in a
               heated Quonset hut.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>In the near future the "green thumb" experts hope to add fresh lettuce, tomatoes,
               onions, and red and green peppers to the local food supply. Nasturtiums, marigolds
               and sweetpeas will satisfy esthetic tastes and brighten the Antarctic camp.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article">
            <ab>AROUND THE BASES: <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName> --
               Construction of "ham" radio shack and hobby lockers in recreation hall 50% completed.
               Hi-fi installation underway. Library and education office cabinets and bookshelves
               80% completed. Installation of fire warning devices in tunnels
                  completed......<placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">NAF McMurdo</placeName> -- Ice runway
               in good condition. April weather summary: Average monthly temp.; -10.5°F;
               monthly high, plus 12°F; monthly low, -33°F.......<placeName ref="#ByrdStation">Byrd Station</placeName> -- Fuel cache covered by two-foot snow
               drift. Flags and bamboo stakes salvaged from old runway for use on new runway in
                  spring.....<placeName ref="#SouthPoleStation">Pole Station</placeName> --
               Observatory interior completed. Interior glaciology cold laboratory 75% completed.
               (Continued next page.)</ab>
            <lb/>
            <fw>--<num type="page" value="2">2</num>--</fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="WilkesStation">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#WilkesStation">Wilkes Station</placeName> -- Minor building and
               equipment repairs proceeding. Over 100 icebergs visible from station. Snow cover now
               zero to 12 feet....<placeName ref="#EllsworthStation">Ellsworth Station</placeName>
               -- April weather summary: Average monthly temp., -9.04°F; monthly high, plus
               24.8°F, on the 4th; monthly low, -34.6°F, on the 9th.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="WilkesStation">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#WilkesStation">WILKES STATION</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-04-29">April 29</date>) -- Through his glasses <persName ref="#OlavLoken">Norwegian Glaciologist Olav Loken</persName> had been studying a
               seal lying on an ice floe in nearby Frogman Cove. He decided definitely it was a rare
               Ross Seal.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Leaving his vantage point on the overhanging rocks he hurried to make known his
               discovery to the other men at the station. At about 2 p.m. <persName ref="#CarlREklund">Station Scientific Leader Carl R. Eklund</persName> of
                  <placeName ref="#AtlantaGA">Atlanta, Ga.</placeName>, came on the intercom system
               and announced the discovery to everyone, stating that an attempt would be made to
               collect the creature for the National Museum.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>From a hill which separates the station from the cove, the men watched <persName ref="#RudolfAHonkala">Rudolf A. Honkala</persName>, Meteorologist, of <placeName ref="#SalisburyNH">Salisbury, N.H.</placeName>, and <persName ref="#DonaldRBurnett">LTJG Donald R. Burnett</persName> of <placeName ref="#MountClemensMI">Mount Clemens, Mich.</placeName>, raise their rifles and
               take careful aim at the seal which was lying on an ice floe about 30 yards out in the
               cove.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Reminding them to be careful not to hit the seal's skull, <persName ref="#CarlREklund">Eklund</persName> gave them the signal to fire. The animal was
               an easy target and died quickly.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Now they were sure the seal itself would not escape, but it began to look like the
               outgoing tide might float the floe out to sea. They had to get a line on the dead
               seal quickly. <persName ref="#RudolfAHonkala">Honkala</persName> and <persName ref="#GarthHStonehocker">Garth H. Stonehocker</persName>, Ionospheric Physicist,
               of <placeName ref="#PortsmouthVA">Portsmouth, Va.</placeName>, dragged a 20-foot
               ladder down to the ice edge, followed by <persName ref="#DuaneJWonsey">Duane J.
                  Wonsey</persName>, Construction Mechanic Constructionman, of <placeName ref="#ElmHallMI">Elm Hall, Mich.</placeName>, and <persName ref="#DavidDaniel">David Daniel</persName>, Commissaryman 3/c, of <placeName ref="#FairfieldTX">Fairfield, Texas,</placeName> carrying coils of line.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Tying the line about him and laying the ladder across the dangerously thin ice,
                  <persName ref="#RudolfAHonkala">Honkala</persName> inched his way toward the floe
               where the dead seal lay. When he reached the floe he cut a hole in the seal's jaw and
               tied the line through it. While he was <choice>
                  <sic>doint</sic>
                  <corr>doing</corr>
               </choice> this <persName ref="#DuaneJWonsey">Wonsey</persName> had gone to get a
               "weasel" which would be used to tow the huge carcass to shore.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>When the treaded vehicle was in position, <persName ref="#DavidDaniel">Daniel</persName>, who had been tending the line to <persName ref="#RudolfAHonkala">Honkala</persName>, secured the line to the rear of the
               weasel. With a wave from <persName ref="#RudolfAHonkala">Honkala</persName>,
                  <persName ref="#DuaneJWonsey">Wonsey</persName> was given the go-ahead. With a
               large splash the rare mammal was hauled from the floe, through the thin ice to
               shore.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>On measuring the seal it was found to be 102 inches long from the tip of his tail to
               his nose. The estimated weight was between 700 and 800 pounds. This was a great day
               for <placeName ref="#WilkesStation">Wilkes Station</placeName> as there have been few
               Ross Seals ever collected.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <ab>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- The setting sun <choice>
                  <sic>brigs</sic>
                  <corr>brings</corr>
               </choice> colder weather at this station and the falling temperature sharply reduces
               outdoor work.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Average mean temperature for April was four degrees colder than last year, seven
               degrees colder than the all-time average, and 12 degrees colder than last month.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Comparison of Fahrenheit temperatures for April at <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName> are as follows: Last year--High, plus 9°; low,
               -53°; mean temperature, -23°. This year--High, plus 10°; low
               -55°; mean temperature -27°. All-time high is plus 27.5°; low,
               -58°; mean temperature, -20°. (Continued next page)</ab>
            <lb/>
            <fw>--<num type="page" value="3">3</num>--</fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="4"/>
            <ab>Average daily fluctuation of temperature during April was 20 degrees: from an
               average daily maximum of -17° to an average daily minimum of -37°.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>Peak wind velocity was slightly lower this year than the all-time record for April.
               This year's was 42 miles per hour, while the all-time April record is 47 mph.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The incidence of cold injury here is very small. There have been only six cases of
               minor frostbite. This is attributed to proper clothing, careful training and good
               judgement of personnel.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="article">
            <p>
                    <choice>
                  <sic>FASCIMILE</sic>
                  <corr>FACSIMILE</corr>
               </choice> TRANSMISSION TO ANTARCTICA -- The first successful transmission of sports
               pictures and Sunday comics to the Antarctic was made on <date when="1957-05-05">Sunday, May 5,</date> via radio facsimile. The transmission was accomplished by
               radio amateurs in the United States, more than 8,000 miles from the point of
               reception.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The pictures were transmitted to the Antarctic by W2KCR at <placeName ref="#NorthSyracuse">North Syracuse, N.Y.</placeName>, and the Operation Deep
               Freeze Committee of the Radio Amateurs of Greater Syracuse as a function of the
               American Red Cross Amateur Radio Morale Message Service. The new radio picture
               transmissions are a forecast of similar and more personal transmissions in the
               future.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Transmission from <placeName ref="#NorthSyracuseNY">North Syracuse</placeName> began
               near midnight Saturday and continued until 6 a.m. that morning. During that time
               several pictures were sent, each requiring an average of 40 minutes for direct
               transmission to <orgName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</orgName>. Transmissions
               included a picture of the recent knockout of middleweight champion Gene Fullmer by
               Sugar Ray Robinson, a Dick Tracy Sunday comic strip and news. Printer's type 1/32 of
               an inch was sent legibly.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The transmission distance was 8,437 miles. Permission was granted to the amateur
               radio Committee by the <orgName ref="#FederalCommunicationsCommission">Federal
                  Communications Commission</orgName> to send facsimile on the 20 meter band between
               14300 and 14350 kilocycles. Atmospheric conditions were reported to be extremely
               difficult by <persName ref="#PaulPBlum">Paul P. Blum</persName>, chairman of the
               committee.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>
                    <persName ref="#GeorgeJDufek">Rear Admiral Dufek</persName> announced this "first"
               for the Antarctic, citing it as both a morale and technical <choice>
                  <sic>cccomplishment</sic>
                  <corr>accomplishment</corr>
               </choice> of benefit to the Navy and to the nation.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>Now that the first amateur radio facsimile attempt has been successfully completed,
               future transmissions are planned for the duration of the <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">International Geophysical Year</orgName>. The
               Navy itself has transmitted radio facsimile to the Antarctic for many months. The
               radio amateurs, however, stress the sending of information that is personal,
               nonofficial, and of a morale nature.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Transmission and reception of facsimiles of family pictures and messages in the
               handwriting of members of the family and other personalized graphics now are
               possible, going both ways between the United States and the Science Station at
                  <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName>.</p>
            <lb/>
            <fw>--<num type="page" value="4">4</num>--</fw>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
