<?xml-model href="ODD/out/AntarcticDraft.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-model href="ODD/out/AntarcticDraft.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter Volume 2 Issue 3</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Florida State University, Office of Digital Research and Scholarship</publisher>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">Attribution 2.0 Generic (CC BY 2.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <placeName>Tallahassee, Florida</placeName>
                  <institution>Florida State University</institution>
                  <!-- INCLUDE (as collection) -->
                  <collection>Robert E. Hancock Jr. Antarctic Collection</collection>
                  <!-- INCLUDE (as iid) -->
                  <idno type="IID">FSU_MSS_1976022_B07_F01_V2I3</idno>
                  =
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <!-- INCLUDE (as title) -->
                     <title>Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter Volume 2 Issue 3</title>
                     <!-- INCLUDE (as author) -->
                     <author>United States. Naval Support Force, Antarctica</author>
                     <!-- INCLUDE  (as docdate; @when)-->
                     <docDate when="1957-04-26">April 26, 1957</docDate>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart>Deep Freeze<figure>
                     <figDesc>A circular illustration of a carpenter bee in cold weather gear
                        holding a variety of tools flying over Antarctical with an onlooking
                        penguin. Above the bee, the acronym IGY is displayed while below it the word
                        DEEPFREEZE is displayed next to a Naval Aviator Insignia</figDesc>
                  </figure>Newsletter</titlePart>
               <titlePart>
                  <cb n="1"/>
                  <bibl>
                     <title>Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter</title>
                     <lb/>
                     <biblScope>
                                <num type="volume" value="2">Volume II</num>, <num type="issue" value="2">No. 2</num> -- <date when="1957-04-19">April 19,
                        1957</date>
                            </biblScope>
                        </bibl>
                  <lb/>
                  <lb/>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine> Phone Liberty 5-6700, Ext. 66675</addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <lb/>
                  <lb/>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Duplicated and distributed by:</addrLine>
                     <lb/>
                     <addrLine>Commander</addrLine>
                     <lb/>
                     <addrLine>Naval Construction Battalions, Atlantic</addrLine>
                     <lb/>
                     <addrLine>Construction Battalion Center</addrLine>
                     <lb/>
                     <addrLine>Davisville, Rhode Island</addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <cb n="2"/>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Commander, U.S. Naval Support</addrLine>
                     <lb/>
                     <addrLine>Force, Antarctica</addrLine>
                     <lb/>
                     <addrLine>Room 214, Bldg. D.</addrLine>
                     <lb/>
                     <addrLine>6th &amp; Independence Ave., SW</addrLine>
                     <lb/>
                     <addrLine>Washington 25, D.C.</addrLine>
                  </address>
                    </titlePart>
            </docTitle>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="1"/>
         <div type="nameplate">
            <head>Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter</head>
            <ab>

                    <num type="volume" value="2">Vol II,</num>

                    <num type="issue" value="3">No. 3</num>


                        <date when="1957-04-26">April 26, 1957</date>

                    </ab>
                    <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <ab>
               <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- The major portion of
               the non-sectarian Easter sunrise service at Little America was dedication of the New
               Richard E. Byrd chapel.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>Services were conducted, commencing at the time the sun rose, at approximately 10
               a.m. However, the service was unique in that the sun set at about the same time the
               service was concluded. Two days after Easter marked the last sunrise until next
               August.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The new chapel is by far the most beautiful building at Little America. All have
               followed its construction with interest. From the laying of its foundations to
               finishing its pews, every task has been done conscientiously, even reverently.
               Volunteers carved the foundation from hard-packed snow on a crisp, clear day when the
               temperature hovered in the minus fifties. Quickly the framework of the 16 by 40 foot
               Jamesway building went up, and was them trimly covered with snug spun-glass insulated
               blanket sections.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p> The chancel section of the chapel is raised six inches above the nave and separated
               by a communion rail exquisitely hand finished. The chancel contains stalls for a
               small choir on the left side, an elevated mahogany altar in the center, the pulpit
               and electronic piano on the right. American and Christian flags flank the altar. The
               altar is dressed with a maroon velour cover bearing the words "Holy Holy Holy" in
               gold across the front piece edged with gold fringe, reversible cross-crucifix,
               matched vases and candlesticks, two seven-branch candelabra, and a missal stand. A
               dossal hanging behind the altar is of heavy blue velour extending from the arching
               ceiling to the deck. Flanking the dossal are white woolen panels reaching to the
               curving walls. The deck is soft green polished tile. The entire chancel area is
               illuminated by concealed overhead floodlights.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The nave is fitted with hand-hewn pews containing built-in kneelers and screens in
               front of the first pew on each side. All woodwork is stained mahogany. The center
               aisle and the area between the pew screens and chancel is green vinyl tile with an
               inlaid cross of white tile centered in the aisle. Remainder of the deck is battleship
               green linoleum. Interior walls are light green with dark olive green framework. The
               chapel will seat approximately 40.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p> Skilled cabinet maker <persName ref="#JohnEReilly">John E. Reilly</persName>,
               builder 1/c, of <placeName ref="#NewOrleansLA">New Orleans</placeName>, assisted by
                  <persName ref="#JackCRees">Jack C. Rees</persName>, construction driver 2/c of
                  <placeName ref="#WestWarwickRI">West Warwick, R. I.</placeName>, designed and
               built the chancel communion rail, and pews, and did most of the interior finishing.
               Supervising construction of the building were <persName ref="#RobertKWhite">Lt. (jg)
                  Robert K. White</persName> of <placeName ref="#GlenFallsNY">Glens Falls, N.
                  Y.</placeName>, and <persName ref="#JulianPGudmunson">Julian P.
                  Gudmunson</persName>, chief builder, of <placeName ref="#StPaulMN">St. Paul,
                  Minn</placeName>. Many other volunteers participated in the construction. All at
               Little America believe <persName ref="#RichardEByrd">Admiral Byrd</persName> would be
               pleased and proud to know that this chapel bears his name.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>(All news items from Little America are prepared by <persName ref="#JohnEZoller">Chaplain John E. Zoller</persName>, Lt., <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">USN</orgName>, of <placeName ref="#ShelbyMI">Shelby, Mich</placeName>.)</ab>
            <fw>(Page <num type="page" value="1">1</num>)</fw>
         </div>
         <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="2"/>
         <div type="article" subtype="NAFMcMurdo">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">NAF MCMURDO</placeName> -- This station played host to
               New Zealanders on Easter Sunday. Eighteen men from the <placeName ref="#NewZealandScott">New Zealand Scott</placeName> base, with their leader
                  <persName ref="#EdmundHillary">Sir Edmund Hillary</persName> of Mt. Everest fame,
               accepted an invitation to Easter dinner and joined U.S. personnel at divine
               services.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p> The chapel, "Our Lady of the Snows," was appropriately decorated with artificial
               Easter lilies. Catholic mass and Benediction of the Blessed Sacrament was offered by
                  <persName ref="#LeonSDarkowski">Father Leon S. Darkowski</persName> of <placeName ref="#PittsburghPA">Pittsburgh, Pa.</placeName> Protestant services were held by
               lay leader <persName ref="#RobertHWakeman">Robert H. Wakeman</persName>, radioman
               2/c. of <placeName ref="#WaltonNY">Walton, N. Y.</placeName>, with <persName ref="#DonaldCHauck">Lt. Donald C. Hauck</persName>, DC, of <placeName ref="#KandiyottMN">Kandiyott, Minn.</placeName>, at the organ.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Other activities included attendance at movies, a hi-fi concert featuring Handel's
               "Messiah," and competitive games in the recreation hall. The guests expressed
               appreciation for the hospitality and invited McMurdo personnel to visit Scott Base.
               The U.S. and New Zealand bases are two miles apart. Much good will has been promoted
               through this exchange of social courtesies.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article">
            <p>AROUND THE BASES -- <placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">NAF MCMURDO</placeName>: Ground
               Control Approach (flight radar) equipment has been disassembled for maintenance. Ice
               runway in good condition. . . . . . <placeName ref="#SouthPoleStation">SOUTH
                  POLE</placeName>: Eight by twelve foot shell for glaciology laboratory has been
               completed. Two Rawinsonde observations (radar tracking of weather balloons) have been
               made daily since <date when="1957-04-15">April 15</date> . . . . . <placeName ref="#ByrdStation">BYRD STATION</placeName>: Tunnel was partially collapsed due to
               the weight of a snow drift . . . . . <placeName ref="#WilkesStation">WILKES
                  STATION</placeName>: Highly successful voice radio contact has been made with
                  <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName>.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="WilkesStation">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#WilkesStation">WILKES STATION</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-04-22">April 22</date>) -- Easy access to the icecap and good surface
               for 50 miles inland indicate ideal conditions for extensive traverse from this
               station. The traverse as projected would provide geophysical and geographical studies
               over one of the greatest unexplored regions of Antarctica.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The proposed trail is from Wilkes along the 110th East Meridian. The primary
               advantage of this route is the presence of fixed stations at the ends and middle of
               the trail to provide control for scientific observations.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>It is proposed the trail operations will begin in late November, using a D-4
               Caterpillar tractor and "weasels," with a second D-4 for partial support. The D-4
               proved effective here pulling 20 tons to the satellite station in land at 4,000 foot
               elevation.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Seismic shots, magnetic observations, and glaciological studies are contemplated at
               intervals of 50 to 75 miles, with gravity and surface meteorological observations at
               10-mil intervals.</ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- Champion "pole sitter"
               at <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName> is <persName ref="#JohnKieffer">John Kieffer</persName>, electronics technical 3/c, of
                  <placeName ref="#NapaCA">Napa, Calif</placeName>. A volunteer to climb antenna
               poles to install insulators and wire, <persName ref="#JohnKieffer">Kieffer's</persName> conquest of nearly fifty poles makes him undisputed
               champ.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Perched atop a pole in minutes fifty degrees weather, buffeted by bitter winds, and
               clumsy in heavy Antarctic clothing, the job is no picnic. Every possible safety
               precaution including spurs, safety belt and boatswain's chair is used.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#JohnKieffer">Kieffer</persName> is an old hand at climbing. Before
               enlisting he had his own set of spurs and cleared fire breaks in the forest of his
               family's property.</p>
            <lb/>
            <fw>(Page <num type="page" value="2">2</num>)</fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="3"/>
            <p>Assisting in the operation is <persName ref="#ThomasEGehringer">Thomas E.
                  Gehringer</persName>, construction electrician 3/c, of <placeName ref="#AllentownPA">Allentown, PA.</placeName>, a veteran lineman. When stationed
               on Guam, prior to volunteering for Deep Freeze, he maintained 150 antenna poles
               ranging 90 to 110 feet high at the Naval Communications Station there.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Gehringer says, "Clinging to the top of a pole in blazing 90-degree sun is quite a
               contrast to doing it at 50 below."</ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- Intense cold plays
               strange tricks on outdoor workers. Dropping into the minus fifties, the chill factor
               is vastly increased by sharp winds. <persName ref="#RichardHills">Richard
                  Hills</persName>, photographer 2/c, of <placeName ref="#FayetteAL">Fayette,
                  Ala.</placeName>, after taking pictures atop a fuel tank, jumped off only to
               discover he couldn't bend his knees. His cold weather trousers had frozen stiff.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Freezing of a more disturbing nature was encountered by <persName ref="#JackCRees">Jack. C Rees</persName>, construction driver 2/c, of <placeName ref="#WestWarwickRI">West Warwick, R. I.</placeName>, and <persName ref="#JohnEZoller">Lt. John E. Zoller</persName>, ChC, of <placeName ref="#ShelbyMI">Shelby, Mich.</placeName> Their nostrils closed up tight with
               ice.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>A screwdriver snapped like glass when pressure was applied. Combustion handwarmers in
               exterior parka pockets went out because the fuel reached a temperature too low to
               burn.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#CalvinLLarson">Calvin L. Larson</persName>, chief photographer, of
                  <placeName ref="#CulbertsonMT">Culbertson, Mont.</placeName>, was unable to
               replace a slide in his plastic plateholder after taking a picture because the
               plateholder contracted in the cold after the slide was removed. He is limited to the
               use of a few wooden plateholders. Film pack, roll and movie film become brittle and
               snap when advanced in the camera.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>VX-6 pilot <persName ref="#HarveyGSpeed">Lt. Harvey G. Speed</persName> of <placeName ref="#NorthMuskegonMI">North Muskegon, Mich.</placeName>, was unable to retract
               skis on his R4D aircraft after takeoff. Engine heat and exhaust vaporized air
               immediately froze on the landing gear and temporarily converted it into "fixed gear"
               type.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Its all in a day's work--but how different from a day's work in the States.</ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article">
            <p>PERSONAL COMMUNICATIONS to and from ANTARCTICA</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Communications between men stationed in the Antarctic and their families in the
               States may be carried out by these methods: (1) Naval Communications Telegrams, and
               (2) "Hamgrams."</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>Telegrams are handled by the <placeName ref="#NavalCommunicationStation">Naval
                  Communication Station</placeName>, Washington 25, D. C. The cost for this service
               is Western Union charges from wherever the telegram is filed to Washington. Under
               ordinary circumstances the following subjects are acceptable or not acceptable:</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Acceptable: (a) Matters of life or death (b) Matters of personal arrangements or
               important personal business, not of a recurrent nature (c) Birth announcements in the
               immediate family.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Not Acceptable: (a) Trivial, indecent or frivilous messages. (b) Holiday or
               anniversary greetings (c) Messages of unnecessary length (d) Ordinary congratulatory
               messages (e) Frequent or recurrent messages pertaining to the conduct of a commercial
               venture. (f) Business solicitations by a commercial enterprise.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <ab>How to address telegrams: Man's name, Rate or Rank, Serial or File No., and
               Antarctic Command. Example: <address>
                        <addrLine>John D. Doe, YNI, 000 00 00;</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>NAF McMurdo;</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>c/o Naval
               Communication Station; Washington 25, D. C.</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </ab>
            <lb/>
            <ab>"Hamgrams" are the type of communication handled by amateur radio operators. "Ham"
               is the slang term for a licensed amateur radio operator. There is no cost for
               messages passed through amateur radio facilities, other than the cost required</ab>
            <lb/>
            <fw>(continued next page) (Page <num type="page" value="3">3</num>)</fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="4"/>
            <ab>to deliver the intended message to the "ham" station operator.</ab>
            <ab>The following address is that of a capable amateur radio operator who has been very
               successful in handling messages to and from Antarctica: <address>
                  <addrLine>
                            <persName ref="#PaulABlum">Paul A. Blum</persName>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>101 Kristin Road, </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                            <placeName ref="#NorthSyracuseNY">North Syracuse, N.
                     Y.</placeName>
                        </addrLine>
               </address>
                </ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>It is sometimes possible to arrange telephone conversations between the States and
               Antarctic bases through the amateur radio facilities. To accomplish this, interested
               parties should address a post card to: <address>
                  <addrLine>
                            <persName ref="#JuliusMJMadey">Julius M. J. Madey</persName>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>1037 Raritan Road,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                            <placeName ref="#ClarkNJ">Clark, New Jersey</placeName>
                        </addrLine>
               </address>Your post card should include person's name and his station in
               Antarctica. The cost of this service will be for long distance phone from where you
               make the call to <placeName ref="#ClarkNJ">Clark, N. J.</placeName>
                </p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The Red Cross has been extremely helpful in effective delivery of messages via ham
               operators between the States and Antarctica. Inquiry should be made of your local Red
               Cross representative for complete details.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- The last of the
               Mohicans has been discovered at <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little
                  America</placeName>. All hands hardly believed what they saw at breakfast the
               other day. Some shook their heads; others rubbed their eyes; all were bewildered.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>In the mess hall were what appeared to be half a dozen Indians. The striking feature
               was the unusual haircut. Each "Indian" had a two-inch crew-cut strip extending from
               the center of his forehead, back across his head top and tapering to a point at the
               base of his neck. All other hair was removed.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The tribal affiliation is unknown, but it's suspected that they may be the last of
               the Mohicans. Much good natured joking and critical observations were made about the
               shape of the heads, bumps, knots and skin texture. There was also some speculation as
               to whether the hair will return. The "Indians" unanimously hope it will.</p>
           <lb/>
            <p>A few new phrases were added to the camp vocabulary, including, "ugh" and "how." It
               was suggested that the aurora-sky watch be alert for smoke signals on the horizon. </p>
           <lb/>
            <p>When asked why such unusual haircuts, <persName ref="#RobertWAnderson">Robert W.
                  Anderson</persName>, electronics technician 3/c, of <placeName ref="WhiteCityKS">White City, Kan.</placeName>, explained "This helps us observe a rule of the
               Antarctic. Never panic--always keep a cool head." He explained that one unexpected
               problem that has developed is placing your head on the pillow in such a fashion as to
               prevent it from sliding off during sleep.</p>
           <lb/>
            <p>Other "Indians" are <persName ref="#CharlesMDarter">Charles M. Darter</persName>,
               chief construction driver, of <placeName ref="#AustinTX">Austin, Texas</placeName>;
                  <persName ref="#KennethAElliot">Kenneth A. Elliot</persName>, construction driver
               1/c of <placeName ref="#FortSmithAR">Fort Smith, Ark.</placeName>; <persName ref="#StevenMuniz">Steven Muniz</persName>, construction driver 2/c, of <placeName ref="#SugarCityCO">Sugar City, Colo</placeName>.; and <persName ref="#JohnAHricsina">John A. Hricsina</persName>, constructionman of <placeName ref="#FranklinPA">Franklin, Pa.</placeName>
                </p>
           <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="NAFMcMurdo">
            <ab>
                    <placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">NAF MCMURDO</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-04-24">April 24</date>) -- A new Antarctic record has been set by Navy aerologists at
               this station.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>A radiosonde balloon (for recording temperature, air pressure and humidity, plus wind
               direction and velocity) sent aloft at 10 minutes past noon remained airborne and was
               tracked until 4:11 p.m., when the signal faded due to battery failure.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The balloon rose to a record 96,276 feet. Temperature at this altitude was minus 87.7
               degrees F. The balloon was 70 miles form the station.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p> The weather equipment was sent up by <persName ref="#ElmerAErdie">Elmer A
                  Erdie</persName>, aerographer's mate 1/c, of <placeName ref="#BuffaloNY">Buffalo,
                  N.Y.</placeName>, and <persName ref="#RonaldWPalmer">Ronald W. Palmer</persName>,
               aerographer's mate 2/c, of <placeName ref="#SeattleWA">Seattle, Wash.</placeName>
               <persName ref="#PalmerCreacy">Palmer</persName> and <persName ref="#AvrilTCreacy">Avril T. Creacy</persName>, aerographer's mate 3/c, of <placeName ref="#GatesvilleTX">Gatesville, Texas</placeName>,</p>
            <lb/>
            <fw>(continued next page) (Page <num type="page" value="4">4</num>)</fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="5"/>
            <p>were on watch when the recordings were made. <persName ref="#BobbyDFancher">Bobby D.
                  Fancher</persName>, aerographer's mate 3/c, of <placeName ref="#CarlsbadNM">Carlsbad, N.M.</placeName>, was off duty at the time and missed the excitement,
               but he will have an opportunity to aim at a new record later.</p>

            <p>Two balloons are released daily, at midnight and noon. <persName ref="#BernardFridovich">Lt. (jg) Bernard Fridovich</persName>, aerology officer,
               of <placeName ref="#NewYorkCityNY">New York City</placeName>, is very proud of his
               men and their work. They spend long hours, sometimes over 20 hours at a stretch,
               getting weather recordings and observations.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="EllsworthStation">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#EllesworthStation">ELLSWORTH STATION</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-04-17">April 17</date>) -- Unlike previous expeditions to Antarctica,
               we now have the use of electricity 24 hours a day for our work and comfort. The one
               primarily responsible for getting this into operation and flawlessly maintaining the
               generators is <persName ref="#JamesLHannah">James. L Hannah</persName>, construction
               electrician 1/c, of <placeName ref="#MemphisTN">Memphis, Tenn.</placeName>
                </p>
           <lb/>
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#EllesworthStation">Ellsworth Station</placeName> was taken over by
               wintering-over personnel in February, with the construction of electrical systems for
               the most part still unfinished. Remaining to be completed was the power house,
               consisting of five generators, wiring connections for the 17 buildings, and wiring
               for the storage tunnel lighting.</p>
           <lb/>
            <p>As the <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavalConstructionBattalions">Seabees'</orgName>
               only electrician, <persName ref="#JamesLHannah">Hannah</persName> was kept busy days
               and often nights with these tasks. Having now completed the electrical systems, he
               has the responsibility of maintaining these systems throughout the year. He also
               maintains the heating systems.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#JamesLHannah">Hannah</persName>, a Texan, began his Navy career in
               1947. He has been a <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavalConstructionBattalions">Seabee</orgName> electrician during his 10 years of service. His foreign service
               has included Alaska, Guam, Cuba, and Africa. Hannah volunteered to come to Antarctica
               because it would be a new experience, and he is one of several who are considering
               remaining here another year.</p>
           <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-04-13">April 13</date>) -- The first bingo party of the year was a
               howling success. Planned by the Little America Senate and supervised by <persName ref="#RobertGAnderson">Lt. Robert G. Anderson</persName> of <placeName ref="#AlamedaCA">Alameda, Calif.</placeName>, the party was started with a "happy
               hour" and buffet supper.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Master of Ceremonies <persName ref="#WilliamJCromie">William J. "Wild Bill"
                  Cromie</persName>, <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">IGY</orgName>
               Glaciologist from <placeName ref="#LongIslandNY">Long Island, N.Y.</placeName>,
               called the bingo, cracked jokes, introduced the floor show, and recited an original
               poem of his own composition entitled, "The Ballad of the Barrier Ledge," a clever
               yarn of dubious dealings on the ice. </ab>
          <lb/>
            <p>Music was provided by "Cumbie's Combo," led by <persName ref="#WilliamACumbie">William A. Cumbie</persName>, aviation electronics technician 2/c, of <placeName ref="#MiltonFL">Milton, Fla.,</placeName> a hoe down expert from away back who
               plays a hot electric guitar. Blowing up a storm on harmonica was <persName ref="#BobbieFGrice">Bobbie F. Grice</persName>, radioman 1/c, of <placeName ref="#HubbardTX">Hubbard, Texas</placeName>. Jazz piano was pounded out by
                  <orgName ref="#EagleScouts">Eagle Scout</orgName>
               <persName ref="#RichardLChappell">Richard L. Chappell</persName>, scientist aid, from
                  <placeName ref="#EggertsvilleNY">Eggertsville, N.Y.</placeName>, and slapping a
               solid, home-made bass was stogie-smoking <persName ref="#EarlRHills">Ens. Earl R.
                  Hills</persName> of <placeName ref="#ChattanoogaTN">Chattanooga, Tenn.</placeName>
               The bass was rigged from a washtub, swab handle, and taut cord.</p>
           <lb/>
            <p>An hilarious impromptu entertainer was <persName ref="#RoccoATaurisano">Rocco A.
                  "Rock" Taurisano</persName>, commissaryman 1/c, of <placeName ref="#CambridgeMA">Cambridge, Mass.</placeName>, sometimes called "The Great Stone Face." His
               impersonation of Hildgarde in falsetto soprano brought down the house. Abundant
               talent and ambitious plans insure many outstanding future parties.</p>
          <lb/>
            <fw>(Page <num type="page" value="5">5</num>)</fw>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
