<?xml-model href="ODD/out/AntarcticDraft.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?><?xml-model href="ODD/out/AntarcticDraft.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter Volume 1 Issue 1</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Florida State University, Office of Digital Research and Scholarship</publisher>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">Attribution 2.0 Generic (CC BY 2.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <placeName>Tallahassee, Florida</placeName>
                  <institution>Florida State University</institution>
                  <!-- INCLUDE (as collection) -->
                  <collection>Robert E. Hancock Jr. Antarctic Collection</collection>
                  <!-- INCLUDE (as iid) -->
                  <idno type="IID">FSU_MSS_1976022_B07_F01_V1I1</idno>
                  =
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <!-- INCLUDE (as title) -->
                     <title>Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter Volume 1 Issue 1</title>
                     <!-- INCLUDE (as author) -->
                     <author>United States. Naval Support Force, Antarctica</author>
                     <!-- INCLUDE  (as docdate; @when)-->
                     <docDate when="1975-04-19">April 8, 1957</docDate>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="1" facs="PLACEHOLDER"/>
         <div type="nameplate">
            <head style="text-decoration: underline; text-align: center; text-transform: uppercase;"
               >Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter</head>
            <lb/>
            <ab>
               <num type="volume" value="2">Volume I,</num>
               <num type="issue" value="2">Issue No. 1</num>
               <date when="1975-04-19">April 8, 1957</date>
            </ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article">
            <p>(EDITORS NOTE: This is the first in a series of newsletters to dependents of men
               wintering over in the Antarctic. Information in the newsletter comes principally from
               material received by radio in Washington. Each base has been asked to file occasional
               stories to let you know what is going on during the winter night in Antarctica.)</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article">
            <div type="article" subtype="incubator">
               <ab type="section-head">OPERATION INCUBATOR</ab>
               <lb/>
               <p><placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> (Delayed) -- (The
                  following story was received from Little America Station via radio messages from
                     <persName ref="#JohnEZoller">Lt. John E. Zoller</persName>, CHC, <orgName
                     ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">USN</orgName>, of <placeName ref="#BonitaSpringsFL"
                     >Bonita Springs, Fla.</placeName>) On <date when="1957-02-16">Feb. 16,
                     1957</date>, an air shipment of fresh eggs from New Zealand arrived at
                     <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName>. While inspecting
                  the eggs <persName ref="#RobertJAdams">Dental Officer Lt. Robert J.
                     Adams</persName>, DC, <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavyReserve">USNR</orgName>,
                  of <placeName ref="#MemphisTN">Memphis, Tenn.</placeName>, wondered if any of them
                  were fertile. Assisted by <persName ref="#WilliamRBurns">William R.
                     Burns</persName>, RM3, <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">USN</orgName>, of
                     <placeName ref="#FlintMI">Flint, Mich.</placeName>, and <persName
                     ref="#BoydDRussell">Boyd D. Russell</persName>, RM3, <orgName
                     ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">USN</orgName>, of <placeName ref="#WacoTX">Waco,
                     Texas</placeName>, they selected six for incubation. Even <persName
                     ref="#RichardHBanasiak">Richard H. Banasiak</persName>, CSI, <orgName
                     ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">USN</orgName>, of <placeName ref="#BallstonLakeNY"
                     >Ballston Lake, N. Y.</placeName>, the cook, approved, perhaps with hope for
                  future fresh eggs and poultry.</p>
               <lb/>
               <p>A Dental Incubator for scientific study of oral flora was utilized. Correct
                  temperature to hatch eggs was unknown. We consulted a research man for a culture
                  of a living virus within the egg. Yesterday, <persName ref="#RobertJAdams">Dr.
                     Adams</persName> handled the eggs. He was elated at two positive embryos and
                  two possible ones. The dental laboratory is now the crossroads of the Little
                  America Station. Everyone wants to see the eggs. Strict visiting hours have been
                  set up. Interest is tremendous and there is much speculation as to sex, color,
                  breed and birthdate of the unborn chick. All hands are anticipating the day the
                  chicken will hatch. Estimated time of arrival is <date when="1957-03-09">March
                     9th</date>.</p>
               <lb/>
               <p>We believe this will be the first chicken ever hatched within the Antarctic
                  Circle. If the chick survives, <persName ref="#RobertJAdams">Dr. Adams</persName>
                  plans to bring the history-making bird home. He says, "Considering the 3,000 mile
                  flight from New Zealand, extended exposure to cold and the age of the egg, this is
                  a miracle". "We almost anticipate the chicken will hatch with earmuffs and
                  mukluks. I am beginning to know how an expectant mother feels".</p>
               <lb/>
               <p>A name is needed for such a fabulous fowl. Friends in the United States are
                  invited to submit suggestions. A progress report will follow next week.</p>
               <lb/>
            </div>
            <div type="article" subtype="incubator">
               <ab>Operation Incubator Progress Report Two (Delayed) -- Preparations continue to
                  welcome eagerly awaited chick. A deluxe corrugated box brooder fitted with the
                  only 25-watt bulb at Little America keeps the temperature at a constant 98
                  degrees. The brooder has an enclosed courtyard for exercise feeding and</ab>
               <lb/>
               <fw>(more-next page-more)</fw>
               <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="2"/>
               <fw type="header">-2- Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter</fw>
               <ab>ventilating.</ab>
               <lb/>
               <p><persName ref="#RobertJAdams">Lt. Adams</persName> narrowly averted a chick
                  catastrophe when the power failed for three hours. Grasping an alcohol blowtorch,
                  he rushed to the rescue and kept the incubator at the proper temperature using
                  candle light illumination. <persName ref="#RobertJAdams">Dr. Adams</persName> is
                  becoming more like a mother hen every day. His face beams every time he handles
                  eggs or discusses the chick.</p>
               <lb/>
               <p>A carefully concocted feed mix includes oatmeal, wheat grain, cornmeal, powdered
                  eggs and milk. Expected chicks drinking water is spiked with terramycin and
                  multiple vitamin complex. A crushed china dish and egg shells will provide
                  roughage since no sand or gravel is available here.</p>
               <lb/>
               <p>The Little America Midwives Association is now an effective organ. They will
                  commence egg inspection every half hour on <date when="1957-03-07">March
                     7th</date> and continue until the blessed event occurs. <persName
                     ref="#RobertJAdams">Dr. Adams</persName> has been designated the attending
                  physician. Midwives are <persName ref="#WilliamRBurns">William R.
                  Burns</persName>, <persName ref="#ThomasGehringer">Thomas Gehringer</persName>,
                  CE3, <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">USN</orgName>, of <placeName
                     ref="#AllentownPA">Allentown, Pa.</placeName>, and <persName
                     ref="#BoydDRussell">Boyd D. Russell</persName>. The poor motherless chick will
                  still need a name. Progress report three will follow next week. </p>
               <lb/>
            </div>
            <div type="article" subtype="incubator">
               <p>Operation Incubator Progress Report Three (Delayed) -- Sadness settled like soft
                  snow over Little America <date when="1957-03-10">March 10th</date> when a tragic
                  communique was issued from sick bay that the baby chick was stillborn.
                  Grief-stricken obstetrician <persName ref="#RobertJAdams">Dr. Adams</persName> and
                  midwives <persName ref="#WilliamRBurns">Burns</persName>, <persName
                     ref="#ThomasGehringer">Gehringer</persName> and <persName ref="#BoydDRussell"
                     >Russell</persName> were nearly prostrate. <persName ref="#RichardHBanasiak"
                     >Banasiak</persName> the cook accepted the news stoically. "It was too much to
                  hope for I guess, fresh eggs and young friers all winter".</p>
               <lb/>
               <p>In the interest of science a post-mortem autopsy was performed by <persName
                     ref="#PatBUnger">Medical Officer Lt. Pat B. Unger</persName>, MC, <orgName
                     ref="#UnitedStatesNavyReserve">USNR</orgName>, of <placeName ref="#MiamiFL"
                     >Miami, Fla</placeName>. He stated, "On close investigation I found an embryo
                  of approximately ten days well formed". "Cause of death undetermined, however,
                  evidence of Big Eye, scourge of the Antarctic, was present". Further investigation
                  is pending.</p>
               <lb/>
               <p>Hope still remains for several other eggs being carefully nurtured in the
                  incubator. Every conceivable precaution has been taken. We are trying to duplicate
                  exactly the care of a mother hen. Eggs are being turned daily. Midwives are
                  practicing how to cluck like a hen. We now have volunteers to massage the eggs
                  with bushy beards in lieu of a caress by a mother hen's feathers. Another progress
                  report will follow next week.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article" subtype="incubator">
               <ab>Operation Incubator Progress Report Four (Delayed) -- No stone has been left
                  unturned in our all out effort to <choice>
                     <sic>insure</sic>
                     <corr>ensure</corr>
                  </choice> that the final dozen eggs left here at <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica"
                     >Little America Station</placeName> by the Coast Guard icebreaker NORTHWIND on
                  her last cruise into the Antarctic produce a live chick. The eggs were transferred
                  from the NORTHWIND to <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America
                     Station</placeName> and carefully handled between the </ab>
               <lb/>
               <fw>(more-next page-more)</fw>

               <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="3"/>
               <fw type="header">-3- Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter</fw>
               <ab>ship and the base by <persName ref="#RobertJAdams">Dr. Adams</persName>. All hope
                  has now been abandoned for the former eggs.</ab>
               <lb/>
               <p>Tender, loving care for the eggs includes daily turning by clucking midwives with
                  fingers covered in feathers from a pillow and daily puzzling with a curly beard by
                     <persName ref="#WilliamFKraut">William F. Kraut</persName>, RM, <orgName
                     ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">USN</orgName>, of <placeName ref="#BridgeportCT"
                     >Bridgeport, Conn</placeName>. Two eggs are being nurtured by <persName
                     ref="#HaroldEButler">Harold E. <choice>
                        <sic>Buelter</sic>
                        <corr>Butler</corr>
                     </choice></persName>, HM, <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">USN</orgName>, of
                     <placeName ref="#EastStLouisIL">East St. Louis, Ill.</placeName>, in a replica
                  of a hen's nest constructed from cotton fixed atop an old steam iron which
                  provides thermostat heat control and humidity. The thermostat failed recently and
                     <persName ref="#HaroldEButler">Butler</persName> became an emergency human
                  incubator, gently cradling the eggs under his arm. The thermostat registers the
                  exact correct temperature. Somewhat surprised, <persName ref="#HaroldEButler"
                     >Butler</persName> asked, "What does that make me"?</p>
               <lb/>
               <p>In order to determine the amount of time to keep the eggs out of the incubator,
                  corresponding to the time a hen would be off the nest, a meticulous stop-watch
                  study of mother hen's routine and actions has been made. For an accurate estimate,
                  guinea pig <persName ref="#HaroldEButler">Butler</persName> attempted to duplicate
                  the exact action of the hen. His comment was, "It sure is different chewing raw
                  oatmeal and tilting my head back to swallow". "I'm glad to do it, but the study
                  was not complete, for some actions which are not native to a hen I cannot
                  duplicate". Progress report five will follow next week.</p>
               <lb/>
            </div>
            <div type="article" subtype="incubator">
               <p>Operation Incubator Progress Report Five (Delayed) -- This is "the long Wait". Day
                  after day the eggs look the same. What goes on inside the eggs is an unseen vital
                  matter. All personnel here are hoping there will be a chick for Easter.</p>
               <lb/>
               <p>Today <persName ref="#RobertJAdams">Dr. Adams</persName> himself handled and
                  turned the eggs gently. He reported some change since handling them a week ago.
                  "Should know for sure if we will have a chick in two weeks", he said.</p>
               <lb/>
               <p>Several days ago <persName ref="#HaroldEButler">Butler</persName> discussed the
                  project via Ham Phone Patch with his father, <persName ref="#RobertFButler">Robert
                     F. Butler</persName>, an ex-farmer of <placeName ref="#EastStLouisIL">East St.
                     Louis, Ill.</placeName>, through the facilities of Ham Radio WOOBJ, <persName
                     ref="#PrestonARichardson">Preston A. Richardson</persName> of <placeName
                     ref="LadueMO">Ladue, Mo</placeName>. <persName ref="#RobertFButler">Mr.
                     Butler</persName> verified the correct temperature, <choice>
                     <sic>freqnency</sic>
                     <corr>frequency</corr>
                  </choice> of turning the eggs and the incubator period but he warned against
                  expecting too much because of the long exposure to cold prior to incubation and
                  the unlikely fact that fertile eggs <choice>
                     <sic>wuuld</sic>
                     <corr>would</corr>
                  </choice> be found in commercial stock for consumption.</p>
               <lb/>
               <ab>Nevertheless, all hands at <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little
                     America</placeName> are doing their utmost in their spare time for
                  success.</ab>
               <lb/>
               <ab>(EDITORS NOTE: The Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter will carry the results of
                  Operation Incubator in its next edition. Final results of the Operation had not
                  been transmitted from Little America at mailing time.)</ab>
               <lb/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <fw>(more-next page-more)</fw>
         <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="4"/>
         <fw type="header">-4- Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter</fw>
         <div type="article" subtype="SouthPoleStation">
            <ab type="section-head">NATIONAL GIN RUMMY TOURNAMENT</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p><placeName ref="#SouthPoleStation">SOUTH POLE</placeName> (Delayed) -- The Last
               Vegas, Nevada, Charities Inc., (National Heart Fund, March of Dimes, Accredited
               Catholic, Protestant and Jewish Charities) sponsored a National Gin Rummy Tournament
               March 7, 8, 9 and 10, using Oswald Jacoby Gin Rummy Rules, From the ranks of
               wintering groups in Antarctica, <placeName ref="#SouthPoleStation">South
                  Pole</placeName> stationed <persName ref="#ChesterWSegers">Chester W.
                  Segers</persName>, CS1, <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">USN</orgName>, was
               selected as a candidate for the tournament.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p><persName ref="#WillieMDickey">Capt. W. M. Dickey</persName>, <orgName
                  ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">USN</orgName>, Commander Naval Support Units, Antarctica,
               stationed at <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName>, offered a
               kingsize Antarctic iceberg as prize in the charity tournament. The tabular berg is
               brand new, having just broken off from the Ross ice barrier. It is approximately 25
               miles long, 10 miles wide and stands about 100 feet above water. The iceberg contains
               an estimated 63 billion tons of ice. We regret that we are unable to deliver the
               berg, although there is no shortage of volunteers to try. If the winner desires to
               pick her up we can guarantee utmost cooperation, especially if the winner is an
               attractive young lady.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p><placeName ref="#SouthPoleStation">South Pole Station</placeName> representative
                  <persName ref="#ChesterWSegers">Segers</persName> was leading <persName
                  ref="#RogerBeck">Roger Beck</persName> of the Los Angeles Mirror in the Gin Rummy
               Tournament when ham radio transmission difficulty forced cancellation of the match.
               Once again the <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">Navy's</orgName> reputation to do
               anything, anytime, anywhere was upheld, <persName ref="#WillieMDickey">Capt.
                  Dickey</persName> offered <persName ref="#RogerBeck">Mr. Beck</persName>
               consolation prize of a miniature kingsize iceberg approximately 100 feet above water.
               The berg contained an estimated 80 million tons of the finest grade of Antarctic ice.
               It is located in the Bay of Whales near <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little
                  America Three</placeName>. We regret we are unable to deliver the berg. However,
               we understand any true Southern Californian can do anything so delivery should be no
               problem for <persName ref="#RogerBeck">Mr. Beck</persName>.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="SouthPoleStation">
            <ab type="section-head"><placeName ref="#SouthPoleStation">SOUTH POLE
                  STATION</placeName> IN WINTER NIGHT</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p><placeName ref="#SouthPoleStation">SOUTH POLE</placeName> (Delayed) -- In a brief
               ceremony <date when="1957-03-24">March 24th</date> the South Pole Station flag was
               lowered, heralding the end of the summer and the beginning of the Antarctic winter
               night. The flag had previously been at half mast in honor of the memory of <persName
                  ref="#RichardEByrd">RADM Richard E. Byrd</persName>. Six months will elapse before
               the eighteen men here at the South Pole will again see the <choice>
                  <sic>suns</sic>
                  <corr>sun's</corr>
               </choice> rays. Prior to the flag lowering ceremony which was observed in minus 80
               degree weather with a chilling 15 knot breeze, a final days outside work by all hands
               completed all major tasks in securing the base for winter. Following a two day
               holiday, a well deserved rest for all, the major emphasis will shift from readying
               the base for the winter to constructing and tunneling, including the digging of a
               1,000 foot tunnel for geomagnetic and seismic programs to be carried out by the nine
               IGY personnel under the direction of station scientific leader <persName
                  ref="#PaulSiple">Dr. Paul Siple</persName>. The nine Navy men here will
               complete</p>
            <lb/>
            <fw>(more-next page-more)</fw>

            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="5"/>
            <fw type="header">-5- Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter</fw>
            <ab>the finishing touches necessary to "batten all hatches" against drifting snow and
               winter temperatures expected to reach a minimum of approximately minus 120 degrees
               and will maintain and operate the base in support of the IGY program.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>Though it will undoubtedly be a long and cold winter, it should also be a busy,
               pleasant and rewarding one for the men of the <placeName ref="#SouthPoleStation"
                  >South Pole Station</placeName> and at the present it is one that is being met
               with top morale and high anticipation.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="NAFMcMurdo">
            <ab type="section-head">LATE <persName ref="#RichardEByrd">RADM RICHARD E.
                  BYRD</persName> HONORED IN ANTARCTICA</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p><placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">NAVAL AIR FACILITY MCMURDO SOUND</placeName> (Delayed)
               -- On <date when="1957-03-17">Sunday March 17, 1957,</date> U. S. Navy personnel at
                  <placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">NAF McMurdo</placeName> honored and paid tribute to
               the memory of a great American, a distinguished Naval officer and world renowned
               explorer, <persName ref="#RichardEByrd">RADM Richard E. Byrd</persName>, in the
               beautiful and picturesque Chapel in the Snow situated on a hill at McMurdo Sound.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>General Memorial Services were conducted and a Catholic Mass was offered in memory
               of the men who during his life made history on this continent as he courageously and
               untiringly uncovered many of its secrets.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>At the General Memorial Service, <persName ref="#RobertHWakeman">Robert H.
                  Wakeman</persName>, RM2, <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">USN</orgName>, of
                  <placeName ref="#WaltonNY">Walton, N.Y.</placeName>, lead the congregation in
               prayer; <persName ref="#JohnWRobertson">John W. Robertson</persName>, SW1, <orgName
                  ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">USN</orgName>, of <placeName ref="#MitchellSD">Mitchell,
                  S. D.</placeName>, read the scriptures and <persName ref="#DonaldCHauck">Lt.
                  Donald C. Hauck</persName>, DC, <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">USN</orgName>,
               base Dental Officer of <placeName ref="#KandiyottMN">Kandiyott, Minn.</placeName>,
               played the organ and lead the singing. <persName ref="#LeonSDarkowski">Lt. Leon S.
                  Darkowski</persName>, CHC, <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">USN</orgName>, base
               Chaplain, reviewed the life of <persName ref="#RichardEByrd">RADM Byrd</persName> in
               a eulogy.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article">
            <ab type="section-head">ANTARCTIC NOTES</ab>
            <p><placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> (Delayed) -- The
                  <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America Station</placeName> plans to
               construct a small worship chapel using volunteer labor. They want to dedicate the
               chapel <date when="1957-04-21">Easter Sunday, April 21st</date>. All hands believe a
               fitting dedicate would be "Richard E. Byrd Memorial Chapel".</p>
            <lb/>
            <p><placeName ref="#EllsworthStation">WEDDELL SEA</placeName> (Delayed) -- <persName
                  ref="#FinnRonne">Capt. Finn Ronne</persName>, Officer-in-Charge of the <placeName
                  ref="#EllsworthStation">Ellsworth Station in the Weddell Sea</placeName> says,
               "all hands are well and expect to have this Station 100 percent operative sometime
               during the first of April.</p>
            <lb/>
            <fw>(more-next page-more)</fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="6"/>
            <fw type="header">-6- Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter</fw>
            <p><placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> (Delayed) -- Health and
               morale is reported high at all seven of the United States Antarctic bases according
               to a report from <persName ref="#WillieFDickey">Capt. W. F. Dickey</persName>,
                  <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">USN</orgName>, Commander Naval Support Units,
               Antarctica.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="7"/>
         <div type="editorialInfo">
            <ab>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <num type="volume" value="1">Vol. 1</num>, <num type="issue" value="2">Issue
                        No. 1</num>, <date when="1957-04-08">8 April 1957</date>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine> Phone Liberty 5-6700, Ext. 66675</addrLine>
               </address>
            </ab>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <ab>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Duplicated and distributed by:</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Commander</addrLine>
                  <lb/>
                  <addrLine>Naval Construction Battalions, Atlantic</addrLine>
                  <lb/>
                  <addrLine>Construction Battalion Center</addrLine>
                  <lb/>
                  <addrLine><placeName ref="#DavisvilleRI">Davisville, Rhode
                     Island</placeName></addrLine>
               </address>
            </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="editorialInfo">
            <ab>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Commander, U.S. Naval Support</addrLine>
                  <lb/>
                  <addrLine>Force, Antarctica, Building "D",</addrLine>
                  <lb/>
                  <addrLine>Sixth &amp; Independence SW</addrLine>
                  <lb/>
                  <addrLine>Washington 25, D.C.</addrLine>
               </address>
            </ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
