<?xml-model href="ODD/out/AntarcticDraft.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?><?xml-model href="ODD/out/AntarcticDraft.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter Volume 2 Issue 4</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="1"/>
         <div type="nameplate">
            <head style="text-decoration: underline; text-align: center; text-transform: uppercase;">Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter</head>
            <lb/>
            <ab>
               <num type="volume" value="2">Vol. II,</num>
               <num type="issue" value="4">No. 4</num>
               <date when="1957-05-03">May 3, 1957</date>
                </ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article">
            <p>Man's ever-present curiosity and interest in world affairs shows itself even in the
               isolated world of Antarctica. At both the <placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">MCMURDO
                  SOUND</placeName> and <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName>
               bases weekly newspapers are being printed.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The enthusiastically received "McMurdo News" contains national and international news
               and station items. There are also a chaplain's corner, "Aerological dartboard"
               (weather summary), doctor's column, and personality profiles.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The Little America Publication is called "The Penguin Post." The paper is
               mimeographed Saturday night and delivered to the barracks and officers' quarters,
               ready for Sunday morning readers. Stateside papers were never devoured more avidly
               than these. With no TV or newsreels, only static-punctuated short-wave, and no
               current U.S. magazines, everyone is parched for news.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>"The Penguin Post" features include "News of the World Beyond US," "News of the World
               Around Us," (Antarctica), sports, science notes, Man of the Week, weather roundup,
               chaplain's column, Letters to the Editor, jokes and cartoons, entertainment, and
               society section (personals). The paper averages eight pages.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Name for the Little America paper was selected by the local Senate. Wide-spread
               interest was indicated by the fact that 85 names were submitted for the paper
               including "Deep Freeze Breeze," "Ice-O-Lated Post," "Crevasse Crier," and "Sastrugi
               Sayings."</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>"Penguin Post" is co-edited by the Navy and IGY men. Editors are <persName ref="#CalvinLLarson">Calvin L. Larsen</persName>, chief photographer's mate, of
                  <placeName ref="#CulbertsonMT">Culbertson, Mont.</placeName>, and <persName ref="#RobertCTaylor">Ronald C. Taylor</persName>, <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">IGY</orgName> Meteorologist, of <placeName ref="#SanGabrielCA">San Gabriel, Calif</placeName>. Reporters are <persName ref="#WilliamFKraut">William F. Kraut</persName>, radioman 1/c, of <placeName ref="#BridgeportCT">Bridgeport, Conn.</placeName>; <persName ref="#BoydDRussell">Boyd D. Russell</persName>, radioman 3/c, of <placeName ref="#FortWorthTX">
                        <choice>
                     <sic>Forth</sic>
                     <corr>Fort</corr>
                  </choice> Worth, Tex.</placeName>; <persName ref="#PaulCDalrymple">Paul C.
                  Dalrymple</persName>, <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">IGY</orgName>
               Glaciologist, of <placeName ref="#CochituateMA">Cochituate, Mass.</placeName>; and
                  <persName ref="#BruceJLieske">Bruce J. Lieske</persName>, <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">IGY</orgName> Meteorologist, of <placeName ref="#SilverSpringsMD">Silver Springs, Md</placeName>. <persName ref="#JohnEZoller">Chaplain John E. Zoller</persName> of <placeName ref="#ShelbyMI">Shelby, Mich.</placeName>, is advisor.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName> is also considering adding
               several "foreign correspondents" to the Post staff in the form of "ham" radio
               operators in various areas of the world.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="article">
            <p>AROUND THE BASES -- (<date when="1957-04-30">April 30</date>) --<placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName>: A 16 by 20 foot gymnasium has
               been completed behind the recreation hall. Heaters have been installed in the
               theatre. Furniture, shelves and cabinets are 20% completed in the library. An R4D of
               VX-6 has made one local flight. A second flight was aborted when the plane's wing tip
               dragged at takeoff, causing minor damage....<placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">NAFMcMurdo</placeName>: Ice runway is in good condition. Ice in channel broken by
               Glacier has reached a thickness of 40 inches......<placeName ref="#ByrdStation">Byrd
                  Station</placeName>: Tunnel which was partially collapsed by snow has been
               repaired and strengthened...<placeName ref="#WilkesStation">Wilkes
                  Station</placeName>: Minor building damage was sustained when 83-knot winds arched
               roofs. </p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-04-29">April 29</date>) -- The <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little
                  America</placeName> "ham" radio station, KC4USA, made an unusual contact recently.
               On <date when="1957-04-14">April 14</date>
               <persName ref="#CarlOWyman">Carl O. Wyman</persName>, <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">IGY</orgName> Ionospheric Physicist, of
                  <placeName ref="#PhiladelphiaPA">Philadelphia</placeName>, received a ham radio
               phone call from friends <persName ref="#FrankLeeming">Frank</persName> and <persName ref="#RuthLeeming">Ruth Leeming</persName> of <placeName ref="#RedBankNJ">Red
                  Bank, N.J.</placeName>
                </p>
            <lb/>
            <fw>(<num type="page" value="1">1</num>)</fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="2"/>
            <p>The unusual feature of the call was that it originated from the <choice>
                  <sic>Leeming's</sic>
                  <corr>Leemings'</corr>
               </choice> 26 foot cabin cruiser at sea off the New Jersey coast. Leeming called a
               telephone operator via marine radio-telephone; the operator called <persName ref="#JuliusMJMadey">Julius M. J. Madey</persName>, operator of amateur station
               K2KGJ in <placeName ref="#ClarkNJ">Clark, N.J.</placeName>; <persName ref="#JuliusMJMadey">Madey</persName> called <persName ref="#BobbieFGrice">Bobbie
                  F. Grice</persName>, radioman 1/c, of <placeName ref="#HubbardTX">Hubbard,
                  Texas</placeName>, who was the radio operator on duty at <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName>; and the radio-telephone contact
               between Leeming and <persName ref="#CarlOWyman">Wyman</persName> was made
               complete.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The "path" was excellent. <persName ref="#CarlOWyman">Wyman</persName> was surprised
               even for the experienced amateur operator that he is. He bought his first crystal
               short wave receiver when a boy, and sold newspapers to pay for it.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>In 1926, when in the <orgName ref="#MarineCorps">Marine Corps</orgName>, he built a
               ham station in Nicaragua and carried some of the first emergency humanitarian traffic
               for service personnel. He was communications officer in the Marines, Pacific Theater,
               during the second World War, and in 1948 he was recalled to Washington for active
               duty with the Electronic Warfare Program. Since release from active duty as a
               Lieutenant Colonel in 1955, he has continued ham radio activities. He holds an
               amateur license number K2VAV.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>At <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName>
               <persName ref="#CarlOWyman">Wyman</persName> will soon start classes for beginners
               desiring to learn code and try for a ham operator's license.</ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="ByrdStation">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#ByrdStation">BYRD STATION</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-04-29">April 29</date>) -- At this isolated, inland base, 647 miles west of <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName>, the last sunrise of the season
               was witnessed on Easter Sunday morning. Special messages were sent and received
               through the courtesy of "ham" radio operators.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>At sunset on Easter Day a tape recording sounded taps and the American flag over Byrd
               station was hauled down for the Antarctic night. There is now a sense of urgency
               about completing the remaining outside work during the few remaining weeks of
               twilight.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="WilkesStation">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#WilkesStation">WILKES STATION</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-04-30">April 30</date>) -- Much activity is centered around the local
               ladder cribbage tournament. Holding the title within a week were <persName ref="#RudolfAHonkala">Rudolf A. Honkala</persName>, <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">IGY</orgName> Meteorologist, of <placeName ref="#SalisburyNH">Salisbury, N. H.</placeName>; <persName ref="#DavidDaniel">David Daniel</persName>, commissaryman 3/c, of <placeName ref="#FairfieldTX">
                        <choice>
                     <sic>Fairfiled</sic>
                     <corr>Fairfield</corr>
                  </choice>, Texas</placeName>; and <persName ref="#CarolREklund">Carl R.
                  Eklund</persName>, station scientific leader, of <placeName ref="#AtlantaGA">Atlanta, Ga.</placeName>
                </p>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#RobertLLong">Robert L. Long, Jr.</persName>, Ionospheric Physicist,
               of <placeName ref="#RochesterNY">Rochester, N.Y.</placeName>, after trying out a ski
               ride behind three dogs, reported considerable disagreement between where he wanted to
               go and where the dogs went. <persName ref="#BillieRLilienthal">Billie R.
                  Lilienthal</persName>, aerographer's, mate 3/c, of <placeName ref="#AshlandNB">Ashland, Nebr.</placeName>, has spent his long night watches making slipcovers
               for our badly soiled lounge chairs.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#SidneyEGreen">Sidney E. Green</persName>, construction driver 3/c, of
                  <placeName ref="#ColbertWA">Colbert, Wash.</placeName>; <persName ref="#EdwardABousquet">Edward A. Bousquet</persName>, utilitiesman 3/c, of
                  <placeName ref="#Worcester">Worcester, Mass.</placeName>; <persName ref="#CarlTBailey">Carl T. Bailey</persName>, Aerographer's mate 3/c, of
                  <placeName ref="#LeeMA">Lee, Mass.</placeName>; and <persName ref="#SheldonWGrinnell">Lt. Sheldon W. Grinnell</persName>, station doctor of
                  <placeName ref="#CarbondaleIL">Carbondale, Ill.</placeName>, have spent Sunday
               holidays helping <persName ref="#CarlREklund">Scientific Leader Eklund</persName>
               with biological field work.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>
                    <persName ref="#GeorgeEMagee">George E. Magee</persName>, builder 1/c of <placeName ref="#MaldenNY">Malden, N.Y.</placeName>, sidelined from his carpentry with a sore
               arm, has been spending much of his time operating the amateur radio station. This has
               helped remove some of the load from <persName ref="#FrederickECharlton">Frederick E.
                  Charlton</persName>, chief electronics technician, of <placeName ref="#MundieIN">Muncie, Ind.</placeName>; <persName ref="#DoinaldLBradford">Donald L.
                  Bradford</persName>, radioman, 1/c,</ab>
            <lb/>
            <fw>(<num type="page" value="2">2</num>)</fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="3"/>
            <ab>of <placeName ref="#MesaAZ">Mesa, Ariz.</placeName>; <persName ref="#KennethJHailstorm">Kenneth J. Hailstorm</persName>, radioman 3/c, of
                  <placeName ref="#GallupNM">Gallup, N.M.</placeName>; and <persName ref="#GarthHStonehocker">Garth H. Stonehocker</persName>, Ionospheric Physicist,
               of <placeName ref="#PortsmouthVA">Portsmouth, Va.</placeName>, who had been hard
               pressed trying to make "ham" radio contacts for station personnel.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#PaulAWyche">Paul A. Wyche</persName>, aerographer's mate 1/c, of
                  <placeName ref="#MaconGA">Macon, Ga.</placeName>, is suffering from a sprained
               ankle. He twisted it while carrying water out to the balloon release shelter.
                  <persName ref="#GilbertLewart">Gilbert Lewart</persName>, <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">IGY</orgName> Seismologist, of <placeName ref="#CloverdaleCA">Cloverdale, Calif.</placeName>, has recorded his first
               earthquake. It came from the area south of Australia.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>
                    <persName ref="#RalphGlasgal">Ralph Glasgal</persName>, <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">IGY</orgName> Auroral Physicist, of <placeName ref="#NewYorkCity">New York City</placeName>, is watching his sleeping hours being
               cut down as the lengthening nights increase the time he must spend making
               observations.</ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-04-24">April 24</date>) -- The long night commenced today. Bidding
               farewell to the sun for the last time until next August, all hands except those on
               duty assembled near the flagpole at 11:15 in the morning for the appropriate ceremony
               of lowering the colors.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>In minus 40 degree temperature and with drifted snow casting long purple shadows in
               the setting sun's almost horizontal orange rays, <persName ref="#BernardFVerboncouer">Bernard F. Verboncouer</persName>, cheif quartermaster, of <placeName ref="#GreenBayWI">Green Bay, Wisc.</placeName>, and <persName ref="#ArthurWBaldwin">Arthur W. Baldwin</persName>, chief radioman, of <placeName ref="#HermosaBeachCA">Hermosa Beach, Calif.</placeName>, lowered the
               blizzard-bitten national ensign at 11:28.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>
                    <persName ref="#JohnEZoller">Lt. John E. Zoller</persName>, Chaplain, of <placeName ref="#ShelbyMI">Shelby, Mich.</placeName>, offered a prayer of thanksgiving for
               divine providence and a petition for continued care on behalf of all men of all
               nations spending the coming winter on teh white continent.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>After the colors were lowered, <persName ref="#HowardJOrndorff">LCDR Howard J.
                  Orndorff</persName>, Officer in Charge of Little America, of <placeName ref="#NutterfortWV">Nutterfort, W. Va.</placeName>, presented the flag to
                  <persName ref="#WillieMDickey">Capt. W. Mills Dickey</persName>, Commander of
               Naval Support Units, Antarctica, of <placeName ref="#RuskTX">Rusk, Texas</placeName>,
               as a memento from all the station personnel. In accepting the flag, <persName ref="#WillieMDickey">Capt. Dickey</persName> said, "This is quite an occasion
               since we will be in the Antarctic only one night. Manana we will be going home. Many
               thanks for the flag. It is somewhat tattered but very well preserved and frosty with
               meaning." He then declared the rest of the day "rope yarn Sunday" (Navy terminology
               for a holdiay).</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Everyone chuckled when the "Orders of the Night" were published (as contrasted with
               the Navy's standard "Plan of the Day."). Examples of the orders include: "Personnel
               caught in the habitat of penguins, skua gulls and seals during daylight hours will be
               punished as a court martial may direct." "Personnel caught casting lights into the
               sky or in any other way competing with aurora studies shall be guilty of
               prefabricating auroras and shall be known as aurora specialists.""All liberty has
               been cancelled for tonight." "These orders will be cancelled automatically upon the
               next rising of the sun."</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Others in the flag-lowering formation were company commanders <persName ref="#JamesEWaldron">LCDR James E. Waldron, Jr.</persName>, of <placeName ref="#NewOrleansLA">New Orleans</placeName>; <persName ref="#HarveyGSpeed">Lt.
                  Harvey G. Speed</persName>, of <placeName ref="#NorthMuskegonMI">North Muskegon,
                  Mich.</placeName>; <persName ref="#RobertKWhite">Lt(jg) Robert K.
               White</persName>, of <placeName ref="#GlennFallsNY">Glenn Falls, N.Y.</placeName>;
               and <persName ref="#PeterARaynolds">Lt(jg) Peter A. Raynolds</persName>, of
                  <placeName ref="#WoodlandHillsCA">Woodland Hills, Calif.</placeName>; and platoon
               leaders <persName ref="#RobertGAnderson">Lt. Robert G. Anderson</persName> of
                  <placeName ref="#AlamedaCA">Alameda, Calif.</placeName>; <persName ref="#EdwardWCamp">Edward W. Camp, Jr.</persName>; chief construction mechanic, of
                  <placeName ref="#DarbyPA">Darby, Pa.</placeName>; and <persName ref="#williamJWilliams">William J. Williams, Jr.</persName>, chief radioman, of
                  <placeName ref="#HarlingenTX">Harlingen, Texas.</placeName>
                </p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Although the sun will not reappear for four months, progressively shortening periods
               of twilight will occur for several weeks. This soft gentle light with predominant
               orange hues creates strikingly beautiful effects upon crystalline texture of the snow
               and ice. This period is popularly referred to as "Indian Summer of the
               Antarctic."</p>
            <lb/>
            <fw>(<num type="page" value="3">3</num>)</fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="4"/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="EllsworthStation">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#EllsworthStation">ELLSWORTH STATION</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-04-28">April 28</date>) -- Radio communication in Antarctica offers a
               challenge to any radioman. This was one of the factors which caused <persName ref="#CharlesWForlidas">Charles W. Forlidas</persName>, radioman 2/c, of
                  <placeName ref="#ClemsonSC">Clemson, S.C.</placeName>, to volunteer for Operation
               Deep Freeze.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>A radioman's work in the Antarctic is not all indoors. In putting up antennas
                  <persName ref="#CharlesWForlidas">Forlidas</persName> and fellow communications
               man, <persName ref="#RobertEHaskill">Robert E. Haskill</persName>, radioman 1/c, of
                  <placeName ref="#NorthHighlandCA">North Highland, Calif.</placeName>, worked in
               temperatures 35 degrees below zero. Now ice continually builds on the antenna wire
               and must be cleared to cut down radio transmission difficulties.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Before radio operations could get underway the radio room, the three transmitters,
               seven receivers and mobile equipment had to be assembled by the operators. Equipment
               intended for shore installations are having to be made to fit and operate. For a
               small station, <placeName ref="#EllsworthStation">Ellsworth</placeName> handles a
               large amount of radio traffic, making necessary an around the clock operation with
               shifts of 12 hours each.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Another job that falls under <persName ref="#CharlesWForlidas">Forlidas</persName>
               and <persName ref="#RobertEHaskill">Haskill</persName> is taking their turns at
               operating the "ham" equipment. Everyone here relies on the skill and patience of our
               radiomen and the "ham" operators in the States who pass personel messages to and from
               our wives and families.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>After his year in the Antarctic, <persName ref="#CharlesWForlidas">Forlidas</persName> is looking forward to returning to <placeName ref="#ClemsonSC">Clemson, S.C.</placeName>, College. He attended there a year
               before joining the Navy.</ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- <persName ref="#HaroldEButler">Harold E. Butler</persName>, hospitalman 1/c, of <placeName ref="#EastStLouisIL">East St. Louis, Ill.</placeName>, is the first man of Deep
               Freeze II to be discharged and reenlisted at <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little
                  America</placeName>. After receiving his honorable discharge, handlebar-moustached
                  <persName ref="#HaroldEButler">Butler</persName> became subject to much
               good-natured ribbing about being a "sandcrab for a day."</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>A lengthy humorous discussion occurred in the messhall, as to whether or not
                  <persName ref="#HaroldEButler">Butler</persName> was entitled to eat there.
                  <persName ref="#WilliamRDenney">William R. Denney</persName>, commissaryman 2/c,
               of <placeName ref="#RaymondWA">Raymond Wash.</placeName>, ruled to feed him without
               charge since he was slated to reenlist the next day. (Legally, a Navyman is a
               civilian for 24 hours between enlistments.)</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#HaroldEButler">Butler</persName> was sworn in by <persName ref="#HowardJOrndorff">Lcdr Howard J. Orndorff</persName>, commanding officer of
                  <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName>, of <placeName ref="#NutterfortWV">Nutterfort, W. Va.</placeName>, for a six-year reenlistment.
               This is his second six-year "shipping over." An enthusiastic career man, <persName ref="#HaroldEButler">Butler</persName> has nine years continuous active duty.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>His primary task here is senior corpsman, assisting the medical and dental officers.
               The doctors say <persName ref="#HaroldEButler">Butler's</persName> excellent
               professional ability is enhanced by a pleasant sense of humor and a sincere concern
               for the welfare of the patients. Prior to coming to the Antarctic, <persName ref="#HaroldEButler">Butler</persName> served three years as a hospitalman with
               the Marine Corps, one year of which was in Korean combat. He then spent over two
               years at the Naval Hospital, <placeName ref="#GreatLakesIL">Great Lakes,
                  Ill</placeName>.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Upon return to the U.S. after his year at <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little
                  America</placeName>, <persName ref="#HaroldEButler">Butler</persName> is aiming
               high. He has requested duty at the White House dispensary.</ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="NAFMcMurdo">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">NAF MCMURDO</placeName> -- Fire destroyed the garage
               building <date when="1957-04-28">April 28</date>. No men were seriously injured.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Estimated cost of the blaze is $106,000. This includes the building proper, a 35-ton
               Caterprillar tractor, a lathe, a saw, an electric drive air compressor,</ab>
            <lb/>
            <fw>(<num type="page" value="4">4</num>)</fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="5"/>
            <ab>a 5-k.w. floodlight trailer, an electric arc welder, two Herman Nelson portable
               heaters, approximately 2500 feet of keying cable and all shop hand and small power
               tools.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <ab>No Deep Freeze II Caterpillar parts were destroyed. Limited special and mechanical
               tools will handicap vehicle maintenance somewhat.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>Cause of the fire has not been determined but an investigation is being made. The
               fire was first discovered at 6:15 a.m. (1:15 p.m., <date when="1957-04-27">Saturday,
                  April 27,</date> EST) and was brought under control four and a half hours
               later.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Construction of a combination panel and quonset rib and canvas lean-to building has
               commenced.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">McMurdo</placeName> is the largest of seven U.S. bases
               in the Antarctic. Its 34 houses are occupied by 87 military personnel during the
               Antarctic winter which began <date when="1957-04-21">April 21</date>. The garage
               building was several hundred feet from the nearest barracks building.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>(<persName ref="#GeorgeJDufek">
                        <choice>
                     <sic>Admiral</sic>
                     <corr>Rear Admiral</corr>
                  </choice> Dufek</persName> said in Washington, "The fire and its losses will not
               affect the accomplishment of our mission for the <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">IGY</orgName> in any way.")</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>Principal mission of the base is tp support air operations. Planes operating from the
               ice airstrip dropped materials to build a science base at the <placeName ref="#SouthPoleStation">South Pole</placeName> during the past Antarctic
               summer.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="#LittleAmerica">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- <persName ref="#JamesEWaldron">Lieutenant Commander James E. Waldron</persName> of
                  <placeName ref="#NewOrleansLA">New Orleans</placeName>, officer in charge of the
               VX-6 detachment here, recently treated everyone to a party celebrating promotion to
               his present rank. Date of rank is retroactive to <date when="1957-02-01">Feb.
                  1.</date>
                </p>
            <lb/>
            <p>First entering the Navy in July 1943, <persName ref="#JamesEWaldron">Waldron's</persName> duty has always been in aviation. After receiving his wings
               in May, 1945, he took advanced flight training, then joined a ferry command until his
               release from active duty the following year.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Volunteering to return to active service in June, 1951, he was ordered to <placeName ref="PensacolaFL">Pensacola, Fla.</placeName>, for helicopter training. <persName ref="#JamesEWaldron">LCDR Waldron</persName> has since logged 1600 hours of
               helicopter flying time, serving aboard seven carriers and making six rescues of
               pilots form the water. In December, 1954, he was rushed to Honduras to participate in
               rescue of flood victims. He flew almost continuously for a week, evacuating survivors
               from roof tops, trees, high ground, and transporting medical aid.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Since coming to Antarctica, <persName ref="#JamesEWaldron">Waldron</persName> has
               piloted aircraft to the Pole twice, to <placeName ref="#ByrdStation">Byrd
                  Station</placeName> four times, plus numerous flights to <placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">McMurdo</placeName>. He is the senior helicopter pilot here.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="WilkesStation">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#WilkesStation">WILKES STATION</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-04-29">April 29</date>) -- On <date when="1957-03-13">March 13</date>
               six men were sitting in a 16-foot-square Jamesway hut that provided living space at
                  <placeName ref="#WilkesStation">Wilkes Station's</placeName> inland icecap
               satellite, They were enjoying an enforced rest period brought on by one of the
               weather phenomena unique in the Antarctic, the "whiteout."</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>The men were <persName ref="#CarlREklund">Carl R. Eklund</persName>, station
               scientific leader of <!--THIS IS INCONSISTENT WITH OTHER SOURCES-->
                    <placeName ref="#MaconGA">Macon, Ga.</placeName>; <persName ref="#RichardLCameron">Richard L.
                  Cameron</persName>, <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">IGY</orgName>
               Glaciologist, of <placeName ref="#BatesvilleCA">Batesville, Calif.</placeName>;
                  <persName ref="#RudolfAHonkala">Rudolf A. Honkala</persName>, <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">IGY</orgName> Meteorologist, of <placeName ref="#SalisburyNH">Salisbury, N.H.</placeName>; <persName ref="#OlavLoken">Olav
                  Loken</persName>, Norwegian Glaciologist; <persName ref="#JohnMolhom">John
                  Molhom</persName>, <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">IGY</orgName>
               Glaciologist, of <placeName ref="#CambridgeMA">Cambridge, Mass.</placeName>; and
                  <persName ref="#PaulFNoonan">Paul F. Noonan</persName>, photographer's mate 1/c,
               of <placeName ref="#DorchesterMA">Dorchester, Mass.</placeName> The "whiteout"
               condition--enveloping</ab>
            <lb/>
            <fw>(<num type="page" value="5">5</num>)</fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="6"/>
            <ab>whiteness and complete lack of horizon--had brought their science studies to a
               standstill.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>They had set out from <placeName ref="#WilkesStation">Wilkes Station</placeName> at
               dawn two days earlier. The site for their satellite station, an important part in the
                  <placeName ref="#WilkesStation">Wilkes</placeName>
               <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">IGY</orgName> program, had to be far
               enough inland for the climate to be representative of the entire icecap, and the snow
               over had to be deep enough to dig a 100-foot pit for glaciological studies.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>By midday they had covered 30 miles after having considerable difficulty getting
               their weasels and sleds over the moraine, a rocky barrier extending along the edge of
               the icecap. Clear weather prevailed until late the following day. After following
               steep trails and experiencing many weasel failures, the party arrived at the 40-mile
               point, about 4,000-foot elevation, and located a site for the inland station.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Erection of the hut was immediately started, while <persName ref="#RudolfAHonkala">Honkala</persName> set up a mast for making meteorological observations.
                  <persName ref="#RichardLCameron">Cameron</persName>, <persName ref="#OlavLoken">Loken</persName> and <persName ref="#JohnMolhom">Molhom</persName> set out ice
               movement stakes for glaciology studies. Then the "whiteout" moved in and all work had
               to be stopped.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>But the inland station had been established. The difficulty of supplying the large
               quantities of fuel that would be needed to operate the inland satellite was discussed <choice>
                  <sic>furing</sic>
                  <corr>during</corr>
               </choice> the period of "whiteout." The impracticability of performing the operation
               with the fast but fragile weasels was generally agreed upon. It was decided that the
               possibility of making a supply trip to the icecap with a D-4 tractor should be
               discussed with <persName ref="#RobertMcIntyre">Robert McIntyre</persName>,
               construction mechanic 2/c, of <placeName ref="#OxnardCA">Oxnard, Calif.</placeName>,
               and <persName ref="#DonaldRBurnett">Lt (jg) Donald R. Burnett</persName>, of
                  <placeName ref="#MtClemensMI">Mt. Clemens, Mich.</placeName>, when they returned
               to <placeName ref="#WilkesStation">Wilkes Station</placeName>.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>On the <date when="1957-03-16">16th</date> weather finally cleared enough to allow
               all to return to the main base, except <persName ref="#RichardLCameron">Cameron</persName> and <persName ref="#OlavLoken">Loken</persName>, who remained
               behind to continue their studies.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="EllsworthStation">
            <ab>
                    <placeName ref="#EllsworthStation">ELLSWORTH STATION</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-05-01">May 1</date>) -- One of the younger members of this station is
               20-year-old <persName ref="#LRLarson">L. R. Larson</persName>, aviation electronics
               technician 3/c, of <placeName ref="#RochesterNY">Rochester, N.Y.</placeName>
                </ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#LRLarson">Larson</persName> came to Deep Freeze following a tour of
               duty aboard the aircraft carrier USS Princeton on the west coast. He learned that Air
               Development Squadron Six was looking for volunteers for the Antarctic trek, and he
               immediately requested the duty.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>His request was accepted and he was sent to <placeName ref="#QuonsetPointRI">Quonset
                  Point, R.I.</placeName>, home of VX-6. A few months later he was aboard the Navy
               cargo ship USS Wyandot, bound for the Weddell Sea.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>Before joining the <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">Navy</orgName> in 1954, Larson
               attended Edison Technical and Industrial high school. After initial Navy training he
               was selected to attend the Navy's Aviation Electronic Technician School in <placeName ref="#MemphisTN">Memphis, Tenn.</placeName>
                </p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Since reaching the Antarctic, <persName ref="#LRLarson">Larson</persName> has
               participated in all phases of the construction of <placeName ref="#EllsworthStation">Ellsworth Station</placeName>, including assembly of two DeHavilland Otter
               aircraft, raising antenna, driving a D-4 tractor and maintenance of the aircraft
               electronic gear.</ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="editorialInfo">
            <p>A misleading statement was published in last week's Newsletter. The record balloon
               observation ascent we reported was a record for the <placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">McMurdo </placeName>base only, not an Antarctic or world record. We regret the
               error.</p>
            <lb/>
            <fw>(<num>6</num>)</fw>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
