<?xml-model href="ODD/out/AntarcticDraft.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?><?xml-model href="ODD/out/AntarcticDraft.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter Volume 2 Issue 2</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Florida State University, Office of Digital Research and Scholarship</publisher>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">Attribution 2.0 Generic (CC BY 2.0)</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <placeName>Tallahassee, Florida</placeName>
                  <institution>Florida State University</institution>
                  <!-- INCLUDE (as collection) -->
                  <collection>Robert E. Hancock Jr. Antarctic Collection</collection>
                  <!-- INCLUDE (as iid) -->
                  <idno type="IID">FSU_MSS_1976022_B07_F01_V2I2</idno>
                  =
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <!-- INCLUDE (as title) -->
                     <title>Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter Volume 2 Issue 2</title>
                     <!-- INCLUDE (as author) -->
                     <author>United States. Naval Support Force, Antarctica</author>
                     <!-- INCLUDE  (as docdate; @when)-->
                     <docDate when="1957-04-19">April 19, 1957</docDate>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="1" facs="PLACEHOLDER"/>
         <div type="nameplate">
            <head style="text-decoration: underline; text-align: center; text-transform: uppercase;">Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter</head>
            <lb/>
            <ab>
               <num type="volume" value="2">Volume II, </num>
                    <num type="issue" value="2"> Issue No.
                  2</num>
               <date when="1975-04-19">April 19,1957</date>
            </ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="ByrdStation">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#ByrdStation">BYRD STATION</placeName> -- At this Antarctic station
                  <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">IGY</orgName> scientists were
               astonished to find ice in the area reaching a depth of 7,800 to 9,750 feet. The
               scientists believe all this ice rests on land but it is not an established fact as
               yet.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="NAFMcMurdo">
            <p>NAF MCMURDO -- During one of many reconnaissance flights in the vicinity of this
               airbase, <persName ref="#SAAntos">Major S. A. Antos</persName>, <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesMarineCorps">USMC</orgName> of <placeName ref="#BuffaloNY">Buffalo, N.Y.</placeName>, discovered what may be an Antarctic phenomenon.
               Situated near Marble Point and the Wilson-Piedmont Glacier, he saw a huge ice tunnel
               more than a mile long. He described it as, "A huge ice tube that looked as if a draw
               were frozen over the top of a cavernous hollow formed by melted glacier ice."</p>
         </div>
         <lb/>
         <div type="article" subtype="SouthPole">
            <p>SOUTH POLE -- The lowest temperature observed thus far at the South Pole is 89
               degrees below zero, recorded on April 2. This temperature exceeded the lowest ever
               recorded in North America -81 degrees observed at Snag, Yukon Territory, Canada, in
               Feb, 1947. It is one degree above the all-time world's record of 90 degrees below
               zero set in northeastern Siberia in Feb. 1933. As late March and early April roughly
               corresponds to September in the Northern Hemisphere, temperatures are expected to
               drop to 120 degrees below zero as mid-winter approaches.</p>
         </div>
         <lb/>
         <div type="article" subtype="WilkesStation">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#WilkesStation">WILKES STATION</placeName> -- The flash of an arm,
               the roar of a cannon, and 1,800 square feet of net took flight in quest of the skua
               gull, a bird of Antarctica. this was immediately followed by the rapid crunching
               sound of men running over hard crusted snow. Such was the scene recently witnessed at
               this station in Vincennes Bay. Perhaps all but one of the persons who witnessed this
               spectacle had never seen anything just like it before. The man whose flashing arm
               gave the signal to fire the salvo was <persName ref="#CarlREklund">Carl
                  Eklund</persName>, scientific leader at this base.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The spectators and participants in this operation saw fire and smoke bellow from
               three cannon muzzles. The muzzles were protruding about 12 inches out of the snow and
               aimed at 20 degrees elevation. But the thing that really amazed the onlookers was the
               sight of the flying net, for through the smoke of the blast the net could be seen
               being carried by the projectiles. In a low arching flight the net carried up and over
               and landed enveloping the gluttonous skuas <choice>
                  <sic>feating</sic>
                  <corr>feasting</corr>
               </choice> on the remains of dead seals.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The setting off of the net resulted in a spontaneous rush of viewers to the scene of
               capture. First to reach the area was <persName ref="#RudolfAHonkala">Rudolf A.
                  Honkala</persName>. <persName ref="#RudolfAHonkala">Rudy</persName> is a U. S.
               Weather Bureau meteorologist stationed here as an assistant to <persName ref="#CarlREklund">Mr. Eklund</persName>. Right on his heels was <persName ref="#SheldonWGrinnell">Lt. Sheldon W. Grinnell</persName>, <orgName ref="#MedicalCorps">MC</orgName>, <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavalReserves">USNR</orgName>, of <placeName ref="#CarbondaleIL">Carbondale, Ill</placeName>.
               With a great deal of zeal, <persName ref="#RudolfAHonkala">Honkala</persName> piled
               onto the net and attempted to grasp one of the trapped birds. His face soon had a
               look of perplexity and he began to wonder if this flurry of wings and claws was going
               to evade his grasp. By then he knew that this was no homing pigeon he was dealing
               with. But the same type of determination that brought him from his home in <placeName ref="#SalisburyNH">Salsibury, N. H.</placeName>, to the Antarctic, he managed to
               capture the bird.</p>

            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="2"/>

            <p>The photographer on the job was <persName ref="#PaulFNoonan">Paul F.
                  Noonan</persName>, photographer first class, of <placeName ref="#BostonMA">Boston,
                  Mass.</placeName> With one continuous movement, <persName ref="#PaulFNoonan">Noonan</persName> planted his camera tripod and shot a scene of <persName ref="#SydneyEGreen">Sydney E. Green</persName>, construction driver 3/c, of Rt.1,
                  <placeName ref="#ColbertWA">Colbert, Wash.</placeName>, brining a captured skua
               gull to <persName ref="#CarlREklund">Mr. Eklund</persName> so the bird could be
               banded. <persName ref="#CarlREklund">Mr. Eklund</persName>, who lives in <placeName ref="#AtlantaGA">Atlanta, Ga.</placeName>, is carrying on this operation in
               conjunction with his biological research in the Antarctic.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The creatures of this land, like the land itself, are quite mysterious to the outside
               world. To study them and their habitat is part of the <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">IGY</orgName> program here. <persName ref="#SheldonWGrinnell">Lt. Grinnell</persName>, assisted by <persName ref="#GarthHStonehocker">Garth H. Stonehocker</persName>, chief ionospheric
               physicist at this station, put the birds in a cardboard carton so that they could be
               weighed. The gloves and heavy clothing worn by the men serve a twofold purpose. They
               not only protect them from the cold but also from the flashing claws and beaks of the
               birds.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>One of the last persons to reach the capture area was <persName ref="#RichardBerkley">Richard Berkley</persName> of <placeName ref="W#WinterParkFL">Winter Park,
                  Fla</placeName>. <persName ref="#RichardBerkley">Berkley</persName>, a
               geomagnetism specialist, manned the detonator which fired the salvo. After all the
               birds were weighted and banded, <persName ref="#CarlREklund">Eklund</persName>
               released the birds. The bringing of the cannons and net from the U.S. had proven its
               merit. This shot, the first of its kind ever made in Antarctica, had netted 13 birds.
               With the knowledge gained from this capture there will be more abundant catches in
               the future.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="EllsworthStation">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#EllsworthStation">ELLSWORTH STATION</placeName> -- A member of this
               station's wintering-over party says Navy cook <persName ref="#EdwardHDavis">Edward H.
                  Davis</persName> of <placeName ref="#ClintonIA">Clinton, Iowa</placeName>, does
               more for morale than all the other base personnel put together. <persName ref="#EdwardHDavis">Davis</persName> rises at 4 a.m. to prepare early breakfast
               and his work isn't completed until 7:30 p.m., after the evening meal. He performs his
               work six days a week with a half day off on Sundays. Due to the heavy work load,
               vigorous atmosphere and tasty cooking Davis turns out, large amounts of food are
               being consumed at <placeName ref="#EllesworthStation">Ellsworth</placeName> and the
               men are continually gaining weight.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#AtlesFLewis">Atles F. Lewis</persName>, aviation metalsmith 1/c, of
                  <placeName ref="#TroyNC">Troy, N.C.</placeName>, has gained 25 pounds in five
               weeks. <persName ref="#EdwardHDavis">Davis</persName> estimates the men are eating
               one and a half times their normal amount of food. They are eating mostly proteins of
               which there consumption is twice that of a Stateside naval base for the same number
               of personnel. In the way of meats, <persName ref="#EdwardHDavis">Davis</persName> is
               serving mostly veal and pork now because it loses its flavor fastest. He is saving
               beef for last. There is enough veal, pork, chicken and liver for two more months.
               Then the fresh meat rations will be supplemented with canned foods. Carbohydrates are
               being consumed one and a half times above normal.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Due to the bitter cold there are lots of coffee breaks and coffee consumption has
               climbed to four times normal. <persName ref="#EdwardHDavis">Davis</persName> believes
               that with the <choice>
                  <sic>comfartable</sic>
                  <corr>comfortable</corr>
               </choice> prefabricated buildings, recreation hall and nightly movies, this is a soft
               life compared with previous Antarctic expeditions. But he maintains he would never
               winter over again and in his own words, "Nothing will look better to me than
               home."</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="WilkesStation">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#WilkesStation">WILKES STATION</placeName> -- During March in the
               Vincennes Bay area, bay waters were still, free of packice. Scientists had begun
               their studies with comparatively little handicap due to the efficient work of
                  <placeName ref="#WilkesStation">Wilkes</placeName> wintering-over <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavalConstructionBattalions">Seabees</orgName>. Glacial geology
               and higher sea levels are being investigated on the Windmill Island group of which
                  <placeName ref="#WilkesStation">Wilkes Station</placeName> is a part. Heavy
               drifting and 10 feet of snow now cover the station.</p>
            <lb/>

            <fw>
                    <num type="page" value="2">2</num>
                </fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- Jack Frost is working
               overtime this year at <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName>. The
               theme song here is "Baby It's Cold Outside." Average temperature during last month
               was 14 degrees colder than last year. Winter is not yet here but it sure feels like
               it. April is also off to a good start. Temperature for the first part of April
               reached 51 degrees below zero.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Personnel are carefully instructed on how to work in such cold weather. Weather is
               announced at reveille, enabling personnel to dress accordingly. When Working
               together, they watch each other for signs of frostbite and other cold weather injury.
               The men welcome coffee breaks which relive them from extended exposure.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>An appendectomy was successfully performed last week by <persName ref="#PatBUnger">Lt. Pat B. Unger</persName>, <orgName ref="#MedicalCorps">MC</orgName>, <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavalReserves">USNR</orgName>, of <placeName ref="#MiamiFL">Miami, Fla.</placeName>, on <persName ref="#AllenEPracht">Allen E.
                  Pracht</persName>, builder 3/c, of <placeName ref="#PittsburghPA">Pittsburgh,
                  Pa.</placeName> Assisting <persName ref="#PatBUnger">Dr. Unger</persName> were
                  <persName ref="#RobertJAdams">Lt. (jg) Robert J. Adams</persName>, <orgName ref="#DamageControlman">DC</orgName>, <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavalReserves">USNR</orgName>, of <placeName ref="#MemphisTN">Memphis, Tenn.</placeName>,
                  <persName ref="#FredAMilan">Fred A. Milan,</persName> physiologist of <placeName ref="#AndoverMA">Andover, Mass.</placeName>, Korean combat veteran <persName ref="#HaroldEButler">Harold E. Butler</persName>, hospitalman 3/c, of <placeName ref="#GigHarborWA">Gig Harbor, Wash.</placeName>
                </p>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#AllenEPracht">Pracht</persName> is reported to be convalescing well
               after the operation. Flashing his usual smile, he said, "It's a relief to have the
               pain gone. I hope to be back on the job soon."</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The first session of the Little America Senate convened recently. This group, part of
               a special services organization, consists of nine senators elected by and from
               station personnel. The purpose of the senate is to afford all hands an opportunity
               through elected representatives to express to the command any comments or suggestions
               about various aspects of the community life. The group also generates plausible ideas
               and plans with special attention towards recreation and education.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Senators are: <persName ref="#HughFBennet">Hugh F. Bennett</persName>, seismologist
               of <placeName ref="#ChipppewaFallsWI">Chippewa Falls, Wis.</placeName>; <persName ref="#RichardLChappell">Richard L. Chappell</persName>, science aide (<orgName ref="#EagleScouts">Eagle Scout</orgName>) of <placeName ref="#EggertsvilleNY">Eggertsville, N.Y.</placeName>; <persName ref="#SLCoyne">S. L. Coyne</persName>,
               construction driver 3/c, <placeName ref="#PiquaOH">Piqua, Ohio</placeName>; <persName ref="#KAElliot">K. A. Elliott</persName>, construction driver 1/c, of <placeName ref="#LancasterPA">Lancaster, Pa.</placeName>; <persName ref="#CWJenkins">C. W.
                  Jenkins</persName>, hospitalman 3/c, of <placeName ref="#GigHarborWA">Gig Harbor,
                  Wash.</placeName>; <persName ref="#WFKraut">W. F. Kraut</persName>, radioman 1/c,
               of <placeName ref="#BridgeportCT">Bridgeport, Conn.</placeName>; <persName ref="#AllenEPracht">A. E. Pracht</persName>, builder 3/c, of <placeName ref="#PittsburghPA">Pittsburgh, Pa.</placeName>; <persName ref="#GHStewart">G. H.
                  Stewart</persName>, aviation machinist's mate 2/c, of <placeName ref="#MinneapolisMN">Minneapolis, Minn.</placeName>; and <persName ref="#EarlTracy">Earl Tracy</persName>, aviation electrician's mate 1/c, of
                  <placeName ref="#GranadaHillsCA">Granada Hills, Calif.</placeName>
                </p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Patterned after the federal government of big America, the Little America special
               services also includes a cabinet, supreme court and president. The cabinet is
               composed of five appointed persons headed by <persName ref="#RichardEHancock">Special
                  Services Officer LCDR R. E. Hancock</persName>, <orgName ref="#SupplyCorps">SC</orgName>, <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">USN</orgName>, of <placeName ref="#AlexandriaVA">Alexandria, Va.</placeName> Others are <persName ref="#JohnEZoller">Chaplain Zoller</persName>, Medical Officer <persName ref="#PatBUnger">Lt. Unger</persName>, and VX-6 member Lt. <persName ref="#RobertGAnderson">R. G. Anderson</persName> of <placeName ref="#AlamedaCA">Alameda, Calif</placeName>. The Supreme Court has three justices: Chief Justice
               is <persName ref="#HJOrndorff">LCDR H. J. Orndorff</persName>, <orgName ref="UnitedStatesNavalReserve">USNR</orgName>, of <placeName ref="#NutterfortWV">Nutterfort, W. Va.</placeName>, Officer in Charge of Little America; <persName ref="#JEWaldron">LCDR J. E. Waldron Jr.</persName>, <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavalReserve">USNR</orgName>, of <placeName ref="#NewOrleansLA">New Orleans, La.</placeName>, Officer in Charge of VX-6; and <persName ref="#APGrary">A. P. Grary</persName>, Deputy Chief Scientist, of <placeName ref="#OakfordPA">Oakford, Pa</placeName>. Purpose of the supreme court is to
               provide counsel of command heads in matters pertaining to the general good and order
               and to approve or disapprove recommendations and initiate action corresponding that
               which the commanding officer would make.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The President is <persName ref="#WillieMDickey">Capt. W. M. Dickey</persName>,
                  <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavy">USN</orgName>, of <placeName ref="#RuskTX">Rusk,
                  Tex.</placeName>, Commander Naval Support Units, Antarctica. He reviews all acts
               of the lower bodies. In a small way, with certain modifications, special services
               operates as a miniature American government. It stimulates interest and provides good
               training in democracy.</p>
            <lb/>
            <fw>
                    <num type="page" value="3">3</num>
                </fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="4"/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="AllBases">
            <p>ALL BASES -- <persName ref="#WillieMDickey">Capt. Dickey</persName> reports from his
               Little America headquarters that radio reports from all U. S. Antarctic bases states
               health and morale excellent. In a request from the stations for items for ships to
               bring down on Deep Freeze III, ping pong balls and sun lamps are big items.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <ab>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- The chapel-library at
               this station, to be called the "Richard E. Byrd Memorial Chapel," has been erected
               and awaits only the arrival of Easter to be officially dedicated.</ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="EllsworthStation">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#EllsworthStation">ELLSWORTH STATION</placeName> -- The
               responsibility of maintenance and repair of heavy duty D-4 and D-8 tractors here
               rests largely on one man, <persName ref="#WalterLDavis">Walter L. Davis</persName>,
               construction mechanic 1/c, of <placeName ref="#BentonCityMO">Benton City,
                  Mo</placeName>. He is the only Navy mechanic here and has six Caterpillar tractors
               and six "weasels" to keep in operation. One of his major jobs on the vehicles so far
               has been getting them started in the 36 degree below zero weather.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The 12 year veteran of Okinawa, Europe and Africa has served as a heavy equipment
               mechanic and is especially suited for the vigorous Antarctic extremes, having served
               in Greenland. A typical day for <persName ref="#WalterLDavis">Davis</persName>
               consists of supplying three buildings with snow which is melted into water. He
               accomplishes this by scooping up the snow with a D-3 tractor and dumping it on the
               roofs of the buildings. Then if the vehicle is in repair he tackles that. If not he
               continues on construction and maintenance of the base. He also maintains and repairs
               the diesel electric generators that supply the base with electricity. <persName ref="#WalterLDavis">Davis</persName> is looking forward to the end of the long
               Antarctic winter night and the return to the United States. He would like a tour of
               recruiting duty. In his own words, "one year down here is long enough."</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="ByrdStation">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#ByrdStation">BYRD STATION</placeName> -- Time goes fast in the
               Antarctic and days are hard to keep up with. Sometimes so much that men even forget
               their own birthdays, as in the case of <persName ref="#JackRFenrod">"Uncle" Jack R.
                  Fenrod</persName>, builder 3/c, of <placeName ref="#WetunkaOK">Wetunka,
                  Okla</placeName>. He entered the mess hall for lunch <date when="1957-04-04">April
                  4</date> after doing some extra work that happened to come up and made him a few
               minutes late. Station cook, <persName ref="#RobertDMarsh">Robert D. Marsh</persName>,
               commissaryman 1/c, of <placeName ref="#NicktownPA">Nicktown, PA.</placeName>, had
               known about his birthday for some time and had been making arrangements which
               included a large devil's food cake with white icing and chocolate lettering. One
               candle was set atop an empty medicine bottle in the center of the table and singing
               by all hands helped create the proper atmosphere for the occasion.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#GordenAbbey">Gorden Abbey</persName>, radioman 1/c, of <placeName ref="#UnionGapWA">Union Gap, Wash.</placeName>, <persName ref="#WELowe">W. E.
                  Lowe</persName>, radioman 1/c, of <placeName ref="#DecaturIL">Decatur,
                  Ill.</placeName>, and <persName ref="#WDWelch">W. D. Welch</persName>, electronics
               technician 3/c, of <placeName ref="#AtlantaGA">Atlanta, Ga.</placeName>, worked most
               of the week in temperatures as low as 68 degrees below zero to construct <persName ref="#WDWelch">Welch's</persName> pet project a rhombic antenna for our amateur
               radio. The antenna was completed and is now receiving some very good signal reports
               from Stateside amateurs.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The Byrd Station Choir, composed of <persName ref="#CEReynolds">C. E.
                  Reynolds</persName>, construction electrician 1/c, of <placeName ref="#wilmingtonDE">Wilmington, Del.</placeName>; <persName ref="#DDBlubaugh">D.
                  D. Blubaugh</persName>, construction mechanic 3/c, of <placeName ref="#UrsinaPA">Ursina, Pa.</placeName>; <persName ref="#JRPenrod">J. R. Penrod</persName>,
               builder 3/c, of <placeName ref="#WetumkaOK">Wetumka, Okla.</placeName>; <persName ref="#RobertDMarsh">R. D. Marsh,</persName> commissaryman 1/c of <placeName ref="#NicktownPA">Nicktown, Pa.</placeName>; and <persName ref="#WesMorris">Wes
                  Morris</persName>, <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">IGY</orgName>
               meteorologist, of <placeName ref="#SaultSte.MarieMI">Sault Ste. Marie,
                  Mich.</placeName>, at the piano, made its first public appearance at Sunday
               religious services and proved a great success.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Quite a few auroral displays have been seen here lately, but the most significant
               one was sighted by <persName ref="#EdwardAAlf">Edward A. Alf</persName>,
               Meteorologist, of <placeName ref="#AppleValleyCA">Apple Valley, Calif.</placeName>,
               while making late evening weather observations. Everyone was awed by its</ab>
            <lb/>
            <fw>
                    <num type="page" value="4">4</num>
                </fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="5"/>
            <ab>ghostly beauty. It looked light green to very pale red, and ran roughly north and
               south, making slow weaving motions.</ab>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <ab>LITTLE AMERICA -- "Operation Incubator" now belongs to the ages.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#RobertJAdams">Lt. (jg) Robert J. Adams</persName>, <orgName ref="#DamageControlman">DC</orgName>, <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavalReserve">USNR</orgName>, of <placeName ref="#MemphisTN">Memphis, Tenn.</placeName>, has
               announced that all hope for the six New Zealand eggs selected for incubation has been
               abandoned. Final <choice>
                  <sic>cnadling</sic>
                  <corr>candling</corr>
               </choice> revealed no growth since last week.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The project provided fun during leisure time and an interesting diversion from duty.
                  <persName ref="#RobertJAdams">Dr. Adams</persName> commented, "In every man there
               remains a trace of the little boy. Perhaps this helps explain why husky <orgName ref="#UnitedStatesNavalConstructionBattalions">Seabees</orgName>, after doing a
               hard day's work, enjoyed trying to raise live chicks for Easter. We appreciate the
               interest and good wishes from our many friends in the States, and regret the project
               was unsuccessful."</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="NAFMcMurdo">
            <ab>
                    <placeName ref="#NAFMcMurdo">NAF MCMURDO</placeName> -- (<date when="1957-04-16">April 16</date>) -- Approach of the Antarctic of the Antarctic night and
               shortened daylight have restricted outdoor work, and a recreation program is in
               effect for whatever leisure time is available.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>An enlisted recreation council was formed and includes <persName ref="#LouisRMaher">Louis R. Maher</persName>, chief electronics technician, of <placeName ref="#OlatheKS">Olathe, Kan.</placeName>; <persName ref="#RichardDHarden">Richard
                  D. Harden</persName>, chief air controlman, <placeName ref="#FortWorthTX">
                        <choice>
                     <sic>Forth</sic>
                     <corr>Fort</corr>
                  </choice> Worth, Tex.</placeName>; <persName ref="#DonaldEBlackenship">Donald E.
                  Blackenship</persName>, builder 1/c, <placeName ref="#HighlandCA">Highland,
                  Calif.</placeName>; <persName ref="#MarcusRiley">Marcus Riley</persName>,
               construction driver 1/c, of <placeName ref="#DanvilleIL">Danville, Ill.</placeName>;
                  <persName ref="#JohnECuster">John E Custer</persName>, machinery repairman 1/c, of
                  <placeName ref="#SpringfieldIL">Springfield, Ill.</placeName>; <persName ref="#HenryJDeeks">Henry J. Deeks</persName>, construction mechanic 1/c, of
                  <placeName ref="#IslingtonMA">Islington, Mass.</placeName>; <persName ref="#JosephJMalla">Joseph J. Malla</persName>, construction electrician 2/c,
                  <placeName ref="#DetroitMI">Detroit, Mich.</placeName>; <persName ref="#AlfredJSwetokos">Alfred J. Swetokos</persName>, aviation machinist's mate
               3/c, <placeName ref="#FlushingNY">Flushing, N.Y.</placeName>; and <persName ref="#RichardCMartin">Richard C. Martin</persName>, aviation electronic technician
               3/c, <placeName ref="#MemphisTN">Memphis, Tenn.</placeName>
                </p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The initiative of the council and the willingness of the men result in a well-rounded
               program. Off duty volunteers have converted a building into a recreation hall,
               complete with ping pong tables, pool, shuffleboard, reading lounge and music.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>An empty quonset hut was made into a gym through the ingenuity of <persName ref="#RobertLFarnam">Robert L. Farnam</persName>, aviation electrician's mate 1/c,
               of <placeName ref="#LewistonID">Lewiston, Idaho</placeName>; <persName ref="#JamesKKennedy">James K. Kennedy</persName>, aviation electronics technician
               3/c, <placeName ref="#CortlandNY">Cortland, N. Y.</placeName>; <persName ref="#MosesLVigil">Moses L. Vigil, Jr.</persName>, aviation machinist's mate 2/c,
                  <placeName ref="#DenverCO">Denver, Colo.</placeName>; <persName ref="#KennethLAlkio">Kenneth L. Alkio</persName>, aviation electronics technician
               2/c, <placeName ref="#EurekaCA">Eureka, Calif.</placeName>; and <persName ref="#EstileGMiller">Estile G. Miller</persName>, airman, of <placeName ref="#BesocoWV">Besoco, W. Va.</placeName> The gym features weight lifting
               apparatus, mats, and a steam bath box operated through a series of coils and an
               overhead drum.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#MarshallFJones">Marshall F. "Rocky" Jones</persName>, photographer
               1/c, of <placeName ref="#VanNuysCA">Van Nuys, Calif.</placeName>, conducts a
               photography class twice weekly after movies. About 20 men sacrifice sleeping time to
               become better shutter bugs.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>
                    <persName ref="#EdwardCSchenketh">Edward C. Schenketh</persName>, parachute rigger
               1/c, of <placeName ref="#FlushingNY">Flushing, N.Y.</placeName>, worked long hours to
               convert an Atwell tent into a hobby shop, stocked with building materials, kids and
               models.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Other activities include movies, weekly bingo, and a one-hour Saturday evening
               social. Each week's program is supplied by the occupants of the respective huts. Last
               Saturday the officers performed courageously as the "Kool Kats" and presented a
               unique program with self-made costumes and repetitive music--they only knew two
               songs.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="SouthPole">
            <ab>
                    <placeName ref="#SouthPole">SOUTH POLE</placeName> -- (Delayed) -- In the ever
               lessening twilight, two weeks after sunset and the beginning of the winter night,
               limited outside work still continues</ab>
            <lb/>
            <fw>
                    <num type="page" value="5">5</num>
                </fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="6"/>
            <ab>at this isolate station. The temperatures, which has been consistently decreasing,
               rose during the day from minus 87 in the early morning to an unseasonably warm minus
               59 at midnight. Winds increased from 13 knots to 26 knots, with gusts up to 31 knots.
               A further rise of both temperatures and winds is anticipated, also a greater amount
               of blowing snow.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <p>As the sun circles the Pole at approximately 6 degrees below the horizon, the earth's
               shadow is seen as a portion of black semicircle along the horizon opposite the sun's
               azimuth, and the Antarctic at twilight remains uniform during a 24 hour period. The
               first stars appeared <date when="1957-03-31">March 31</date> and now are seen in
               increasing numbers.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>At low temperatures exhaled breath emits a characteristic crackling roar like steam
               escaping from an open valve and creates light fog throughout the tunnels. Outside
               work of any type is increasingly difficult as temperatures drop. Altitude
               (approximately 9,200 feet) causes more rapid breathing than normal when heavy work is
               being done. Cold air burns the throat and chest necessitating a shorter pace with
               frequent breaks to catch your breath and resume normal breathing.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>The main tunnel at the <placeName ref="#SouthPoleStation">South Pole
                  station</placeName> will be approximately 12 feet beneath the surface, six feet
               wide and eight feet high, with branch tunnels off the sides at regular intervals.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Approximately 150 cubic feet of snow is required each day to be melted for drinking
               water and other uses. The snow will be man-hauled from now on due to the fact that
               cold weather precludes the use of tractors or weasels for hauling it. All vehicles
               are in hibernation for the winter.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Despite the seemingly bleak aspect of our present environment, it is one of constant
               interest to all. Even in minus 80 degree weather, personnel have been able to work
               outside for up to three hours at a stretch without undue discomfort. Time passes
               quickly and morale continues to be high in anticipation of a successful year.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="EllsworthStation">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#EllsworthStation">ELLSWORTH STATION</placeName> -- The air support
               for <orgName ref="#InternationalGeophysicalYear">IGY</orgName> activities here is
               being accomplished with two DeHavilland Otter aircraft and one HO4S helicopter. Here
               again in the great Antarctic continent, responsibilities must fall upon a few.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Such is the case of <persName ref="#AtlesFLewis">Atles F. Lewis</persName>, aviation
               mechanics for the Otter aircraft stationed here. In Antarctica each flight requires
               the flight mechanic to spend approximately three hours working on the aircraft prior
               to take-off. The facilities with which to work are few, and each plane must have the
               snow brushed from it, the ice melted, the engine pre-heated and the fuel for the most
               part pumped by hand, in addition to giving regular engine checks.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Although many flights have been flown already, the main support program will begin in
               September, during the next Antarctic spring. With the planes safely put away from the
               winter months, Lewis will be busy setting up shop and helping separate supplies
               stored in the aviation building.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>In October <persName ref="#AtlesFLewis">Lewis'</persName> present enlistment will
               expire, and he will be the first man to reenlist here. He has already decided on the
               next duty he desires. First he wants to go to flight engineers school and then to
               Hawaii for duty as a flight engineer on a Super Constellation.</p>
            <lb/>
            <fw>
                    <num type="page" value="6">6</num>
                </fw>
            <pb facs="PLACEHOLDER" n="7"/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="LittleAmerica">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">LITTLE AMERICA</placeName> -- This Station intends to
               secure its helicopter for the winter due to the frigid weather. All aircraft have
               been put away for the winter except one Otter and one R4D. Construction of Kiel
               airfield antenna farm is underway. Health and morale at <placeName ref="#LittleAmerica">Little America</placeName> is excellent. Only 25 per cent of
               the cargo deposited on the ice barrier by DF II supply ships still remains there. The
               other 75 per cent has been safely returned to the Station.</p>
            <lb/>
         </div>
         <div type="article" subtype="EllsworthStation">
            <p>
                    <placeName ref="#EllsworthStation">ELLSWORTH STATION</placeName> -- Items and
               amounts, food-wise, for the wintering-over party here have been satisfactory with few
               exceptions. It is recommended, though, that in the future there be less rabbit,
               prunes, rhubarb, collard greens, and frankfurters, and more popcorn.</p>
            <lb/>
            <ab>New items recommended for next year's wintering party include fresh frozen carrots,
               dill pickles, canned honey, chocolate chips, dehydrated cabbage, glazed citron peel,
               and vanilla extract tablets.</ab>
            <lb/>
            <ab>A few utensils and table-ware items that might be useful are serving forks and
               spoons, one bolt of turkish toweling, doughnut cutters, 96 boxes of tooth-picks,
               three dozen ash trays, and 50 Christmas menus.</ab>
         </div>
         <div type="editorialInfo-1" rend="left-align">
            <ab>Operation Deep Freeze Newsletter</ab>
            <lb/>
            <ab>
                    <num type="volume" value="2">Volume II</num>, <num type="issue" value="2">No.
                  2</num> -- <date when="1957-04-19">April 19, 1957</date>
                </ab>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <ab>
               <address>
                  <addrLine> Phone Liberty 5-6700, Ext. 66675</addrLine>
               </address>
            </ab>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <ab>Duplicated and distributed by:</ab>
            <lb/>
            <ab>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Commander</addrLine>
                  <lb/>
                  <addrLine>Naval Construction Battalions, Atlantic</addrLine>
                  <lb/>
                  <addrLine>Construction Battalion Center</addrLine>
                  <lb/>
                  <addrLine>Davisville, Rhode Island</addrLine>
               </address>
                </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="editorialInfo-2" rend="right-align">
            <ab>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Commander, U.S. Naval Support</addrLine>
                  <lb/>
                  <addrLine>Force, Antarctica</addrLine>
                  <lb/>
                  <addrLine>Room 214, Bldg. D.</addrLine>
                  <lb/>
                  <addrLine>6th &amp; Independence Ave., SW</addrLine>
                  <lb/>
                  <addrLine>Washington 25, D.C.</addrLine>
               </address>
                </ab>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
